Developmental Psychology © 2011 American Psychological Association 2012, Vol. 48, No. 1, 257–270 0012-1649/11/$12.00 DOI: 10.1037/a0025402
Longitudinal Effects of Theory of Mind on Later Peer Relations: The Role of Prosocial Behavior
Marcella Caputi, Serena Lecce, Robin Banerjee
and Adriano Pagnin University of Pavia
University of Sussex
Children’s peer relations represent a key aspect of school adjustment. However, little is known about their social-cognitive precursors. To address this gap, the authors followed 70 children across the transition to primary school. At Time 1 (age 5), Time 2 (age 6), and Time 3 (age 7), children were assessed on their theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and verbal ability. In addition, at Time 2 and at Time 3, the authors gathered peer nominations. Results supported the authors’ mediational hypothesis of indirect paths from early theory of mind to subsequently lower peer rejection and higher peer acceptance, via improvements in prosocial behavior. The authors discuss implications of these longitudinal effects for the understanding of the impact of social-cognitive achievements for children’s developing social relations.
Keywords: theory of mind, peer relationships, prosocial behavior
Theory of mind refers to the ability to recognize the existence of mental states and to predict and explain social behavior on the basis of these mental states (Astington, 1993; Wellman, 1990). Almost 30 years of research in this area have shown not only the existence of a dramatic improvement in theory of mind during preschool years (Wellman, Cross, & Watson, 2001) but also sub- stantial individual differences between children of the same age (Cutting & Dunn, 1999; Repacholi & Slaughter, 2003). In the present article, we investigated whether and how individual dif- ferences in children’s theory of mind predict later children’s rela- tionships with peers. More precisely, we examined the role of prosocial behavior in mediating the association between early theory of mind and later peer relationships.
The study of the relation between children’s theory of mind and their social interactions represents a hot topic in developmental psychology. There are several basic reasons for expecting a link between mind reading skills and social variables. As Hughes and Leekam highlighted in a highly cited article, “theory-of-mind skills transform and/or are transformed by children’s close relationships” (Hughes & Leekam, 2004, p. 590). Theoretically, the existence of a close link between children’s theory of mind and social relation- ships fits with the social constructivist approach (Astington & Olson, 1995; Carpendale & Lewis, 2004; J. Dunn, 1996; K. Nel- son, 1996). Notwithstanding some specific differences in their theoretical formulations, these authors all propose a model of children’s development that explicitly emphasizes the construction of social understanding within the context of social interactions.
This article was published Online First September 5, 2011.
Marcella Caputi, Serena Lecce, and Adriano Pagnin, Department of Psychology, University of Pavia, Italy; Robin Banerjee, School of Psy-
chology, University of Sussex, United Kingdom.
Correspondence concerning this article should be addressed to Marcella
Caputi, Department of Psychology, University of Pavia, P.zza Botta 6, 27100 Pavia, Italy. E-mail: marcella.caputi@unipv.it
According to this approach, children’s development of theory of mind should not be understood simply in terms of the growth of their own cognitive abilities, but rather should be regarded as inextricably tied to children’s participation in social exchanges with other people. Support for this view comes from studies showing that children with positive relationships with parents (Meins et al., 2002; Ruff- man, Perner, & Parkin, 1999) and siblings (J. Dunn, Brown, Slomkowski, Tesla, & Youngblade, 1991; Hughes, Fujisawa, En- sor, Lecce, & Marfleet, 2006) perform better on theory-of-mind tasks. A similar effect is likely to be found for peer relationships, which constitute a relevant context in children’s social life before (Brown, Donelan-McCall, & Dunn, 1996; Hughes & Dunn, 1997) and during the school years (Ladd, 1999). Indeed, the peer context offers unique opportunities to understand that people can have a different point of view on the same situation (Banerjee, 2004; Zerwas, Balaraman, & Brownell, 2004). The complex interplay between theory of mind and peer relationships has recently been underlined by the results of a recent study by Banerjee, Watling, and Caputi (in press), which show evidence of a cyclical relation- ship between mind reading (faux pas understanding) and peer relations during the primary school years.
Despite the progress in theoretical and empirical work described above, the existing literature on theory of mind and social rela- tionships is at present rather limited and far from conclusive. In addition, much of the evidence for the importance of theory of mind for social competence comes from studies in children with autism, for whom the mentalizing deficit provides a potential explanation for problems in social interaction and communication (Peterson, Garnett, Kelly, & Attwood, 2009; Tager-Flusberg, 2003).
Studies on typically developing children are relatively few in number, and we are only just beginning to piece together the connections between social cognition and social relations. In one of the first studies on this topic, Dockett (1997) tested 3- to 5- year-old children on their theory of mind and measured their
 257
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

258
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
degree of popularity using peer nominations. As expected, the author reported a significant association between the two variables. Compatible results were found in another sample of 3- to 5-year- olds by Peterson and Siegal (2002). They showed that rejected children (receiving high numbers of least-like [LL] and low num- bers of most-like [ML] peer nominations) scored lower than pop- ular children (high on ML and low on LL) on a battery of theory-of-mind tasks.
However, the links between peer relations and theory-of-mind skills have been rather tenuous in other studies. For example, Slaughter, Dennis and Pritchard (2002) examined the relations between children’s theory of mind and their level of social pref- erence (calculated as the difference between positive and negative nominations) and social impact (calculated as the sum of positive and negative nominations). The researchers reported that theory of mind predicted social preference only for children older than 5 years of age; in addition, they did not find any significant effect of theory of mind on children’s peer status over and above the effect of verbal intelligence. Similarly, Badenes, Estevan, and Bacete (2000) reported a heterogeneous pattern of associations between theory of mind and peer relations. More precisely, they found few differences in theory of mind among popular, average, and rejected boys and girls: Popular girls scored higher than average or ne- glected girls on a deception task, and rejected boys older than 6 years showed a poorer understanding of white lies. Even more strikingly, Garner, Curenton, and Taylor (2005) reported no sig- nificant association between theory of mind and teachers’ rating of children’s social competence. They measured false-belief under- standing and positive and negative behaviors with classmates in a socially diverse sample of preschoolers; the authors found a lack of correlation between these variables when age, socioeconomic sta- tus, and language were taken into account.
Considered altogether, the empirical studies discussed above show that there is no clear consensus on whether and how theory of mind is related to children’s relationships with peers. The inconsistency of findings is likely to relate to both methodological and theoretical issues. One interesting possibility concerns the age of participants. Results from the studies presented above and from other studies with older children (Banerjee et al., in press) seem to indicate that theory of mind could become more important for peer relationships as children increase in age. According to the social constructivist approach, this result can be interpreted considering the increasing importance of peer relationships as children grow up and enter the school arena. However, it is also possible that a certain degree of theory-of-mind ability is necessary before chil- dren can capitalize on these skills in order to improve their social relationships with peers. Thus, it seems plausible that theory of mind might confer benefits to social relations after rather than before 5 years of age, paralleling the myriad social and cognitive challenges posed by children’s transition into primary school (McIntyre, Blacher, & Baker, 2006).
Another intriguing plausible explanation is proposed by Baner- jee and Watling (2005) and by Astington (2003), who argued that standard theory-of-mind tasks (first- and second-order false-belief tasks) represent situations that are quite different from real-life circumstances in which children are required to use mentalizing abilities. Thus, first- and second-order false-belief tasks do not necessarily involve exactly the same kind of social understanding that is necessary to build positive social relationships. According
to this view, other more “ecologically valid” theory-of-mind mea- sures such as the faux pas task (Banerjee et al., in press) and the strange stories task (Baron-Cohen, Jolliffe, Mortimore, & Robert- son, 1997; Happe ́, 1994) are expected to show closer connections with children’s interpersonal relationships. The strange stories task evaluates children’s ability to understand nonliteral utterances, such as sarcasm and irony; the faux pas task measures children’s understanding of mental states involved in unintentional insults. This task requires children to detect and identify faux pas in a number of hypothetical vignettes, to answer a comprehension question about the faux pas, and to identify the false belief that led to the faux pas. Understanding a faux pas is particularly important in children’s everyday life as recently shown by Banerjee and colleagues (in press), who reported significant associations be- tween peer rejection and poorer understanding of faux pas in children aged between 7 and 11 years.
Another interesting explanation has been recently advanced by Hughes (2011). She affirms that the lack of a strong and clear association between children’s theory of mind and their peer relationships could reflect a theoretical rather than methodological issue. Considering the profound discrepancy that may exist be- tween having an ability and using it in real-life situations, Hughes argues that we cannot expect children with good theory of mind (as indexed by classic and advanced tasks) to always use their knowl- edge in a similar way when interacting with peers. We argue that such a perspective is very significant in consolidating the socio- constructivist approach, because it helps us understand how theory of mind is not only constituted but also applied within social relationships. Thus, the theory-of-mind-built-in-context perspec- tive needs to be combined with the theory-of-mind-used-in-context perspective in order to better understand the link between mind reading and peer relationships.
Such a model is particularly intriguing because it implies that the link between theory of mind and peer relationships is not simply direct, but is likely to be mediated by other variables. In the present study, we adopt this view by considering, among all the possible factors, the mediating role of prosocial behavior. It is defined as a series of actions that benefit others and indicate a concern for the well-being of another person, such as helping, sharing, comforting, and cooperating (Weir & Duveen, 1981). Our rationale for concentrating on prosocial behavior as a key medi- ating variable comes from previous evidence for a strong link between the frequency of prosocial acts and both peer relationships and theory-of-mind understanding at this age (Slaughter et al., 2002). On the one hand, children who frequently engage in proso- cial acts are more likely to show high levels of cooperative play with friends in preschool (J. Dunn & Cutting, 1999), to build sincere friendships after the transition to primary school (J. Dunn, Cutting, & Fisher, 2002), and to be popular among their peers (Denham, McKinley, Couchoud, & Holt, 1990). On the other hand, children who tend to display low levels of prosocial behavior are often rejected by their peers (Parkhurst & Asher, 1992). Inter- estingly, this association was found not only in preschoolers but also in young adolescents (Pakaslahti, Karjalainen, & Keltikangas- Jarvinen, 2002).
Furthermore, children’s level of prosocial behavior, in turn, appears to be predicted by their social understanding. Being able to put oneself in another child’s shoes seems to be a fundamental prerequisite for prosocial behavior (Eisenberg & Mussen, 1989).
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

Consistent with this view, children who score higher on theory- of-mind measures, such as emotion-understanding, perspective- taking, and false-belief tasks, are more likely to frequently engage in prosocial behaviors (Dekovic ́ & Gerris, 1994; Denham, 1986; Denham et al., 1990; Lalonde & Chandler, 1995; D. Nelson & Crick, 1999; Slaughter at al., 2002; Strayer, 1980). Thus, children whose advanced mind reading skills make them particularly sen- sitive to what the other children think and feel are also particularly good at helping and comforting others.
The Present Study
In the empirical work reported here, we focused on the transition to school as it is “one of the first rights of passage children experience in their formative years” (McIntyre et al., 2006, p. 349). At school entry, children are faced with heightened demands for well-regulated and goal-directed activities, including sustained behavioral inhibition, compliance with rules, and the capacity to initiate and sustain positive interpersonal relationships with teach- ers and peers (Campbell & von Stauffenberg, 2008; Kellam, Re- bok, Ialongo, & Mayer, 1994). Together, these factors have been recently considered equally important for children’s school read- iness. Indeed, Denham (2006) and Mashburn and Pianta (2006) have redefined this construct highlighting the importance of chil- dren’s social-emotional competence and social relationships in shaping developmental trajectories within the school context.
We addressed the key methodological and theoretical issues identified above by (a) considering the social-cognitive achieve- ments of children as they navigate the transition to primary school (from ages 5 to 7 years); (b) using a wide range of age-appropriate theory-of-mind tasks; (c) investigating–among the many possible mechanisms that might contribute to the relationship between theory of mind and relationship with peers—children’s prosocial behavior as a mediator; and (d) considering the possibility of distinctive links with peer acceptance versus rejection.
Crucially, we investigated these associations between children’s theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and peer relationships using a longitudinal design. It seems possible that some of the ambiguities in previous research stem from a failure to consider effects of theory of mind on peer relations over time. Although a cross- sectional approach is obviously less time-consuming, it can reveal only a small portion of the mosaic. Thus, in the present study, we followed a group of children from the last year of preschool through the second year of primary school. Longitudinal measure- ment of the key variables across multiple time points allowed us to conduct cross-lagged analyses that reveal whether and to what extent a given variable (e.g., theory of mind) can predict changes over time in other variables (e.g., peer relations). In addressing such an issue, we also wanted to control for verbal ability, because prior research has suggested links with theory of mind (Milligan, Astington, & Dack, 2007), social competence (Putallaz, 1983) and prosocial behavior (Slaughter et al., 2002).
Overall, the present study had two main hypotheses, based on our theoretical formulation. First, we expected to find a longitu- dinal association between early theory of mind and later peer relationships, independently of the role of verbal ability. Second, we hypothesized indirect paths from early theory of mind to subsequent peer relationships, via differences in prosocial behav- ior. In evaluating these two hypotheses, we suggest that a full
understanding of the mediating role of prosocial behavior in the connection between theory of mind and peer relations entails a separate consideration of peer acceptance and rejection (Newcomb & Bukowski, 1983). Whereas peer acceptance is reflected in the number of ML peer nominations received by a child, peer rejection is reflected in the number of LL nominations received.
Unfortunately, very few studies have adopted a perspective that differentiates acceptance and rejection, and this limits our under- standing of how theory of mind might be precisely connected with interpersonal relations. However, the rationale for looking sepa- rately at these two dimensions is strengthened by the results of work showing that acceptance and rejection, despite being mod- erately related one another, are not polar opposites (Bukowski, Sippola, Hoza, & Newcomb, 2000). In particular, Bukowski and colleagues found a high level of heterogeneity in rejection at the low end of acceptance and vice versa. Furthermore, Banerjee et al. (in press) found more consistent links between faux pas under- standing and peer rejection rather than peer acceptance. However, they also cautioned that the connections with peer acceptance need to be examined in further research, because both low levels of acceptance and high levels of rejection are conceptually plausible correlates of children’s interpersonal and social-cognitive difficul- ties. The present study offers an opportunity to investigate subtle distinctions related to this issue at a crucial age, when children are negotiating peer interactions during the transition to school.
It should be noted that this study, by tracing developmental trajectories connecting theory of mind and peer relations in Italian children, is one of relatively few that involve children from non- English-speaking Western countries. This is a relevant issue from both a theoretical and an empirical point of view as it speaks to the nature/nurture debate in theory-of-mind development. Previous research has shown that Italian children lag behind their British counterparts between 5 and 6 years of age (Hughes et al., 2011; Lecce & Hughes, 2010) and during preadolescence (Lecce & Hughes, 2009). In the present study, we build on previous studies by evaluating theoretically driven hypotheses about how individ- ual differences in Italian children’s theory of mind are connected with their social profiles.
Method
Participants
A sample of 84 Italian children was recruited via kindergartens and also invited to participate 12 and 24 months later; the present analyses are based on the 70 children (39 boys) for whom com- plete data were available for the key variables of this study. It should be noted that data on theory of mind at Time 1 in a subsample (67%) of these children were also examined in a cross- cultural study by Lecce and Hughes (2010). Children were 5 years old (M 􏰀 67.25 months, SD 􏰀 4.32 months, range 􏰀 54–75 months) at Time 1, 6 years old (M 􏰀 78.31 months, SD 􏰀 3.07 months, range 􏰀 72–84 months) at Time 2, and 7 years old (M 􏰀 90.14 months, SD 􏰀 3.19 months, range 􏰀 83–96 months) at Time 3. The schools were located in the city of Pavia (North of Italy) and surrounding towns, in areas with mixed socioeconomic back- grounds. At Time 1, children were attending 12 different kinder- gartens (15 classes): 10 public schools (12 classes), and two private schools (three classes). At Time 2, children moved to 17
THEORY OF MIND AND PEER RELATIONS
259
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

260
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
different primary schools (20 classes): 16 public schools (19 classes) and one private school (one class). At Time 3, children did not change schools. All the children were of Caucasian origin and native Italian speakers. No participant was clinically referred for cognitive or learning difficulties.
With regard to parental occupation, 19.05% of the fathers were in professional/managerial occupations, 34.92% were in skilled nonmanual occupations, and 46.03% were in manual occupations or unemployed; 12.31% of the mothers were in professional/ managerial occupations, 56.92% were in skilled nonmanual occu- pations, and 30.77% were in manual occupations or unemployed. With regard to parental education, 29.69% of fathers and 27.69% of mothers had a university degree, 31.25% of fathers and 47.69% of mothers had the equivalent of A-levels (i.e., high school di- ploma), and 39.06% of fathers and 24.62% of mothers had the equivalent of General Certificates of Secondary Education. On the basis of parental education and occupation, socioeconomic status was estimated for each child through the procedure described by Hollingshead (1975). Children’s socioeconomic status was distrib- uted as follows: 17.46% medium-low category, 19.05% medium category, 49.21% medium-high category, and 14.29% high cate- gory. In terms of family structure, 37.05% of the children were singletons, 50.00% had one sibling, 10.94% had two siblings, and 1.56% had three siblings.
Procedure
Data collection took place every year between March and April, at the end of the spring term. Parental written consent was obtained at each time point. To obtain consent, a letter explaining the study was delivered to the parents by the teachers. About 95% of the contacted families gave consent to participate in the study. At every time point, each child was individually administered a bat- tery of theory-of-mind tasks and a verbal ability task. The tasks were counterbalanced for order over the testing occasions across children. In addition, two teachers rated children’s prosocial be- havior at all time points. Finally, peer sociometric nominations were collected after the transition to primary school (i.e., at Time 2 and Time 3) when children had known each other, respectively, for at least 7 and19 months. The entire class for each participating child provided peer nominations (total n 􏰀 501).
Design
At Time 1 and Time 2, children completed a battery of theory- of-mind tasks (first-order and second-order false belief, and mixed emotion understanding) previously used by Hughes and colleagues (Hughes et al., 2000) and a verbal ability test (Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test Revised [PPVT]; Dunn & Dunn, 1981). At Time 3, children were administered the Theory of Mind Test (TMT; Pons & Harris, 2002) and the Test of Emotion Comprehension (Pons & Harris, 2000) as measures of theory of mind, and the Test for Reception of Grammar (TROG; Bishop, 1982) as a measure of verbal ability.
As for prosocial behavior, at each time point two teachers were asked to complete together for each child the Cooperation subscale from the Social Skills Rating System (SSRS; Gresham & Elliott, 1990) and the Pro-social scale from the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ; Goodman, 1997). At Time 2 and Time 3,
teachers also completed the Prosocial With Peers subscale from the Child Behavior Scale (CBS; Ladd & Profilet, 1996).
Finally, at Time 2 and Time 3, children’s peer rejection and popularity were measured using the sociometric nominations in the context of the classroom.
Measures
Theory of mind: False-belief understanding (Time 1 and Time 2). Following the procedure suggested by Hughes and colleagues (2000), two standard first-order false-belief tasks were administered: an unexpected content (Wimmer & Hartl, 1991) and an unexpected transfer task (Wimmer & Perner, 1983). In each task, children were credited with 1 point if they correctly answered both the experimental and the control question. Ttwo second-order false-belief stories were also administered on the basis of the simpler second-order task developed by Sullivan, Zaitchik, and Tager-Flusberg (1994). Each story involved a first- and a second- order false-belief question as well as control reality questions. In each story and for each type of false-belief question (first- and second-order), children were credited with success (1 point) only if they passed both the test and the control question. Finally, two belief-desire reasoning tasks were administered, presenting either a nice surprise or a nasty surprise (Harris, Johnson, Hutton, An- drews, & Cooke, 1989). Each story involved a first-order false- belief and then an emotion-based-on-false-belief question as well as control reality questions. Again, children were credited with success (1 point) only if they passed both the test and the control question. Therefore, possible total scores range from 0 to 10.
Theory of mind: Mixed emotion understanding (Gordis, Rosen, & Grand, 1989) (Time 1 and Time 2). Children’s understanding of emotions was assessed using six stories of a storytelling interview. In the first “explain” set, children were told three stories, in which it was made explicit that the protagonist felt two conflicting emotions, and children were asked to explain why the character felt each emotion. In the second “infer 􏰁 justify” set, children were told three stories and asked both to infer and explain how the character felt. Children’s answers were scored: 0 for no emotion explained/stated, 1 for one emotion, or 2 for two opposite- valence emotions. Possible scores therefore ranged from 0 to 12 points.
TMT (Pons & Harris, 2002) (Time 3). The TMT consists of a book with a scenario on every page. The test is divided into 10 blocks, each made up of three items, to give a total of 30 items presented in a fixed order. Each block evaluates a specific com- ponent of theory of mind (Flavell, 2004): (a) Level 1 perspective taking; (b) Level 2 perspective taking; (c) Understanding of inten- tionality; (d) Understanding of ignorance; (e) Understanding of first-order false belief; (f) Understanding of the distinction be- tween appearance and reality; (g) Understanding of lies; (h) Un- derstanding of jokes; (i) Understanding of second-order false be- lief; (j) Understanding of double-bluff. Of 30 items, 22 were administered: two items for components (a)–(h) and three items for components (i) and (j), which are particularly informative given the age of the participants. The administration procedure is divided into two steps. The experimenter, while showing a drawing, reads the corresponding story regarding the depicted characters, and the
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

child is asked to give an answer choosing between two options. Scores could range from 0 to 22 points.
Theory of mind: Test of Emotion Comprehension (TEC; Pons & Harris, 2000) (Time 3). The TEC has a structure very similar to the TMT. It comprises a book (A4 format) with a scenario in the upper part of each page, in which the faces of the depicted characters are left blank. The experimenter, while show- ing the picture, reads the corresponding story and asks the child to infer the emotional state of the character choosing from four facial expressions. These expressions represent four possible emotions (two positive and two negative) of the character. The test is divided in nine blocks, presented in a fixed order, which evaluate nine components of emotion understanding: (I) Emotion understanding based on facial expression; (II) Understanding of external causes of emotion; (III) Emotion understanding based on desires; (IV) Emotion understanding based on beliefs; (V) Understanding of the influence of a reminder on the present emotional state; (VI) Un- derstanding of the capacity to control a felt emotion; (VII) Under- standing of the capacity to hide an emotion; (VIII) Understanding of mixed emotions; (IX) Understanding of moral emotions. Fol- lowing the authors’ scoring system, 1 point is credited to the investigated component by answering correctly all the questions in a block. Score range 􏰀 0–9.
Prosocial behavior. As anticipated, at each time point, two teachers were asked to complete jointly, for each child, the Coop- eration subscale of the Elementary version of the SSRS (Gresham & Elliott, 1990). This subscale is made up of 10 items based on a 3-point scale (scores range 􏰀 0 –20). In addition, they filled in the five-item Pro-social scale of the SDQ (Goodman, 1997) on a 3-point scale (scores range 􏰀 5–15). Finally, at Time 2 and Time 3, teachers also completed the seven-item Prosocial With Peers subscale of the CBS (Ladd & Profilet, 1996) on a 3-point scale (scores range 􏰀 7–21).
Peer nominations (Coie, Dodge, & Coppotelli, 1982) (Time 2 and Time 3). Each child was given a list of the classmates (with names in random order) and asked to identify the names of three peers whom he or she most liked (ML) and three peers whom he or she least liked (LL). ML and LL nominations received by every child were standardized within each classroom. Peer nominations were provided by the entire class of each participating child. Care was taken to instruct children in the confidentiality of responses.
Verbal ability: PPVT-R (L. M. Dunn & Dunn, 1981) (Time 1 and Time 2). This test measures children’s receptive lan- guage. The experimenter reads a word and presents four pictures to the child, who is then asked to point to the picture that best represents the word (e.g., “Can you show me the dog?”).
Verbal ability: TROG (Bishop, 1982) (Time 3). This test focuses on grammar structures, giving us a more inclusive measure of language ability and therefore serving as a more stringent control for verbal ability in our analyses. The child is asked to choose a picture from four alternatives that best corresponds to the meaning of the word or sentence read aloud by the experimenter. The test comprises 80 items, divided into 20 blocks, presented in a fixed order. Each block contains four items that measure the same syntactic ability. In the present research, we took into consideration the total number of blocks passed (range 􏰀 0–20).
Results
We begin by presenting preliminary results on data reduction strategies for the construction of an overall index of theory of mind and prosocial behavior at each time point. For each of these aggregates, we provide Cronbach’s alpha as a measure of internal consistency. Next, we present descriptive statistics before turning to the main hypothesis of the study. We computed correlations between variables both within and across time and then used AMOS software for structural equation modeling (using criteria for assessing model fit from Hu & Bentler, 1998, 1999) to evaluate longitudinal associations between theory of mind, prosocial be- havior, and peer nominations. Separate analyses were undertaken for the prediction of ML and LL nominations in order to allow for distinct patterns regarding the precursors of peer acceptance and peer rejection.
Data Reduction and Preliminary Analyses
At each time point, we constructed an aggregate measure of children’s theory of mind by standardizing the score for each task and then summing these standardized scores. Cronbach’s alphas indicated that the internal consistency of the theory-of-mind ag- gregate was acceptable at Time 1 (􏰂 􏰀 .71), and adequate though modest at Time 2 (􏰂 􏰀 .66) and at Time 3 (􏰂 􏰀 .64). These values were not affected by the deletion of single items indicating that each task equally contributed to the aggregate score. The construc- tion of theory-of-mind aggregates was supported by the results of two further separate analyses. First, a factor analysis using varimax rotation yielded a single factor explaining 47%, 43%, and 57% of the variance at Times 1, 2, and 3, respectively. Factor loadings were larger than .54 at Time 1, .41 at Time 2, and .53 at Time 3. Second, the correlations between false-belief and social outcomes at each time point (prosocial behavior at Time 2, peer acceptance and peer rejection at Time 3) were not significantly different in strength from the corresponding correlations for emotion under- standing (z 􏰙 1.13, ns, 95% CIs [􏰃.14, .49], [􏰃.28, .38], [􏰃.36, .29]) at Time 1; (z 􏰙 .58, ns, 95% CIs [􏰃.25, .40], [􏰃.23, .41], [􏰃.41, .24]) at Time 2; and (z 􏰙 1.60, ns, 95% CIs [􏰃.55, .06], [􏰃.20, .44], [􏰃.53, .08]) at Time 3. Given these results, we used an aggregate of theory of mind at all three time points. Similarly, we constructed an overall index of children’s prosocial behavior at each time point by summing the standardized scores for the vari- ous subscales listed in the Method section. Internal consistency was good at Time 1 (􏰂 􏰀 .72) and excellent at the last two time points (􏰂 􏰄 .94).
Table 1 shows the descriptive statistics for the components of each construct at every time point. Considerable variation in per- formance on the theory-of-mind and verbal ability tasks was evident at each time point; in addition, a wide range of individual differences was apparent for teachers’ ratings of prosocial behav- ior. Results showed that less than 3% of children performed at ceiling on false-belief and verbal ability tasks at all time points; between 10% and 18% performed at ceiling on emotion under- standing. Regarding teachers’ rating of prosocial behavior, be- tween 7% and 31% of children were evaluated at ceiling on single subscales. However, when we consider the aggregate score distri- bution, the percentage of children scoring at ceiling noticeably diminished: 0% at Time 1, 7% at Time 2, and 6% at Time 3.
THEORY OF MIND AND PEER RELATIONS
261
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

262
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
Table 1
Means, Standard Deviations, and Range of Possible and Actual Scores of Theory of Mind (ToM), Prosocial Behavior (PB), and Verbal Ability (VA) Measures at all Time Points
 Measure
Time 1
ToM: False-belief understanding ToM: Emotion understanding PB: Cooperation subscale (SSRS) PB: Pro-social scale (SDQ)
VA: PPVT
Time 2
ToM: False-belief understanding
ToM: Emotion understanding
PB: Cooperation subscale (SSRS)
PB: Pro-social scale (SDQ)
PB: Prosocial With Peers subscale (CBS) VA: PPVT
Time 3
ToM: False-belief understanding
ToM: Emotion understanding
PB: Cooperation subscale (SSRS)
PB: Pro-social scale (SDQ)
PB: Prosocial With Peers subscale (CBS) VA: TROG
M (SD) 5.17 (2.00)
9.21 (1.91) 16.40 (2.61) 11.47 (2.12) 76.36 (16.47)
6.56 (1.74)
9.77 (1.49) 16.03 (4.39) 12.13 (2.38) 16.39 (3.43) 90.83 (18.60)
17.61 (1.78) 7.09 (1.42) 16.63 (4.12) 11.82 (2.52) 16.37 (3.67) 15.47 (2.51)
Possible range Actual range
0–10 1–10 0–12 3–12 0–20 9–20 5–15 7–15 0–175 49–114
0–10 3–10 0–12 6–12 0–20 3–20 5–15 6–15 7–21 7–21 0–175 51–133
0–22 14–22 0–9 2–9 0–20 6–20 5–15 6–15 7–21 8–21 0–20 9–20
  Note. SSRS 􏰀 Social Skills Rating System; SDQ 􏰀 Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire; PPVT 􏰀 Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test; CBS 􏰀 Child Behavior Scale; TROG 􏰀 Test for Reception of Grammar.
A series of independent-samples t tests showed no significant gender differences on theory of mind at Time 1, t(68) 􏰀 0.74, ns, d 􏰀 0.35, 95% CI [􏰃0.99, 0.45]; at Time 2, t(68) 􏰀 1.06, ns, d 􏰀 0.26, 95% CI [􏰃1.02, 0.31]; and at Time 3, t(68) 􏰀 1.14, ns, d 􏰀 0.28, 95% CI [􏰃1.11, 0.30]; on peer acceptance at Time 2, t(68) 􏰀 1.07, ns, d 􏰀 0.26, 95% CI [􏰃0.24, 0.78]; and at Time 3, t(68) 􏰀 0.53, ns, d 􏰀 0.13, 95% CI [􏰃0.34, 0.58]; on peer rejection at Time 2, t(68) 􏰀 1.92, ns, d 􏰀 0.47, 95% CI [􏰃0.01, 0.80]; and at Time 3, t(68) 􏰀 0.74, ns, d 􏰀 0.18, 95% CI [􏰃0.24, 0.52]; on verbal ability at Time 1, t(68) 􏰀 0.36, ns, d 􏰀 0.09, 95% CI [􏰃6.58, 9.51]; at Time 2, t(68) 􏰀 1.43, ns, d 􏰀 0.35, 95% CI [􏰃2.52, 15.22]; and at Time 3, t(68) 􏰀 1.29, ns, d 􏰀 0.30, 95% CI [􏰃1.97, 0.42]. The only significant gender differences
Table 2
were found on prosocial behavior at Time 1, t(68) 􏰀 􏰃2.48, p 􏰅 .05, d 􏰀 0.57, 95% CI [􏰃0.93, 􏰃0.10]; and at Time 3, t(68) 􏰀 2.13, p 􏰅 .05, d 􏰀 0.52, 95% CI [􏰃2.50, 􏰃0.08], with boys (Time 1:M􏰀􏰃0.45,SD􏰀1.49;Time3:M􏰀􏰃0.46,SD􏰀2.64)rated as showing less prosocial behavior than girls (Time 1: M 􏰀 0.56, SD􏰀1.96;Time3:M􏰀0.83,SD􏰀2.35).
Associations Between Variables
Before commenting on the main results, we report the correla- tions among all the variables considered in the study as a prelude to our model testing. As shown in Table 2, individual differences in verbal ability, theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and peer
Zero-Order Correlations Between Theory of Mind (ToM), Prosocial Behavior (PB), Most-Like Nominations (ML), Least-Like Nominations (LL), and Verbal Ability (VA) at Each Time Point (T1, T2, and T3)
 1. T1 ToM 2. T1 PB 3. T1 VA 4. T2 ToM 5. T2 PB 6. T2 ML 7. T2 LL 8. T2 VA 9. T3 ToM
10. T3 PB 11. T3 ML 12. T3 LL 13. T3 VA
—
.05 —
.35 .14 —
.34 􏰃.03 .13 —
.34 .22 􏰛􏰛 †
􏰃.06 .28 .27 .35 􏰛􏰛 † 􏰛􏰛
.37 􏰃.31 .29 􏰛 􏰛
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13
 􏰛􏰛􏰛􏰛􏰛􏰛†
􏰛􏰛􏰛􏰛
􏰛􏰛 􏰛 􏰛
.34 .05 .15
—
.20 .09 .02 .07
—
􏰃.30 .21 .18 .33
􏰛􏰛􏰛†􏰛 􏰛
.29 􏰃.30 .03 􏰃.08 .70 .20 .30 .19 􏰃.14 .28
—
􏰃.14 􏰃.32 􏰃.22 .62 􏰃.19
􏰛􏰛 􏰛􏰛 􏰛􏰛 † 􏰛􏰛􏰛
􏰛􏰛 􏰛 􏰛
􏰃.04 .18 .36 .29 .30 􏰃.19 .14 􏰛􏰛 † 􏰛􏰛 􏰛 􏰛􏰛􏰛
􏰃.36 .22 .16 .36 .29 􏰃.50 .16 􏰛† 􏰛􏰛􏰛
􏰃.25 .21 .06 .11 .55 􏰃.18 .04
􏰃.13 —
􏰛􏰛 􏰛 􏰛􏰛􏰛
.31 .31 .33 􏰃.20 .44 ††
— .23 .06
􏰃.07 .22 􏰛􏰛􏰛
— .44 —
􏰛􏰛􏰛
􏰃.44 .18 􏰛􏰛
􏰃.37 .12 — 􏰃.15 —
 Note. TI, T2, T3 􏰀 Time 1, Time 2, and Time 3.
† 􏰛 􏰛􏰛 􏰛􏰛􏰛
p 􏰅 .10. p 􏰅 .05. p 􏰅 .01. p 􏰅 .001.
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

nominations were all stable across time points (mean rT1-T2 􏰀 .45, p 􏰅 .01; mean rT2-T3 􏰀 .47, p 􏰅 .01). Interestingly, individual differences in theory-of-mind performance show significant sta- bility over 1-year time periods even after the stability of individual differences in verbal ability is taken into account (partial r 􏰚 .31, p 􏰀 .01); the correlation between Time 1 and Time 3 approached significance (partial r 􏰀 .21, p 􏰀 .08). Table 2 also shows that verbal ability and theory of mind were significantly associated only at Time 1, and not at subsequent time points. However, there is no significant contrast in the strength of this association across time points (z 􏰅 1.06, ns). Verbal ability, moreover, is correlated neither with prosocial behavior nor with peer nominations within any time point, indicating a separate trajectory for this type of language, in comparison with social behavior and relationships. Overall, early verbal ability is significantly related with social outcomes at Time 3. Here it is also important to note that teachers’ and peers’ evaluations of children’s social relationships (prosocial behavior and sociometric nominations, respectively) show a good concordance both at Time 2 and Time 3.
Regarding the associations between the key variables of this study, Table 2 illustrates that although the measures of theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and sociometric nominations were not consistently associated within each time point, there was a clear pattern of correlations among these variables over time, as pre- dicted. Specifically, Time 1 theory of mind was associated with Time 2 prosocial behavior, which in turn was associated positively with Time 3 ML nominations and negatively with Time 3 LL nominations. Interestingly, a test comparing the absolute value of the correlation between Time 2 prosocial behavior and Time 3 ML nominations (.29) with the absolute value of the correlation be- tween Time 2 prosocial behavior and Time 3 LL nominations (.50) showed a difference approaching statistical significance (p 􏰅 .09).
In our main analysis, we used structural equation modeling to examine cross-lagged associations among the variables from Time 1 to Time 2 and from Time 2 to Time 3, taking into account the stability of each variable over time and any variance explained by verbal ability. Following recommendations by Hu and Bentler (1999), we used the following absolute fit indices (suitable for models with samples smaller than 250 subjects): the Steiger’s root-mean-square error of approximation (RMSEA), the compar- ative fit index (CFI), and the standardized root-mean-square resid- ual (SRMR). Regarding the RMSEA, values below .05 indicate a
very good fit, and those below .10 indicate a reasonable fit (Steiger, 1990); regarding the CFI, values above .95 indicate good fit and between .90 and .95 an acceptable fit (Bentler, 1990); finally, the SRMR needs to be below .08 to indicate a good fit (Hu & Bentler, 1998). We also report the chi-square, which should ideally not be significant in a good model, as it indicates no significant difference between the postulated model and the real data. It should be noted that verbal ability was included in our analyses as a control variable, predicting all scores at all the time points. We also allowed error terms for prosocial behavior, ML, and LL nominations to covary within time points, to allow for potential unmeasured variables that could have influenced these relationships.
We conducted separate modeling analyses for predicting LL nominations and for predicting ML nominations in order to track specific pathways related to peer acceptance and peer rejection, respectively. In each case, we began with a model including all autoregressive and cross-lagged paths and then removed the non- significant paths. This resulted in the two models shown in Figure 1 (predicting LL nominations) and Figure 2 (predicting ML nominations). For both models, we obtained a reasonable fit. The values for the LL nominations model were as follows: 􏰆2(34, N􏰀)􏰀36.72,p􏰀.344,CFI􏰀.982,RMSEA􏰀.034,SRMR􏰀 .063; the values for the ML nominations model were as follows: 􏰆2(34, N 􏰀 70) 􏰀 37.20, p 􏰀 .324, CFI 􏰀 .968, RMSEA 􏰀 .037, SRMR 􏰀 .067. As outlined before, the values of chi-square, CFI, RMSEA, and SRMR demonstrated good fit. Results show that theory of mind at each time point predicted increased prosocial behavior at the subsequent time point. With regard to the predic- tion of sociometric nominations, the two models showed distinc- tive patterns. Specifically, prosocial behavior at each time point predicted decreased LL nominations at the subsequent time point. However, prosocial behavior predicted increased ML nominations only from Time 2 to Time 3, and there was also an additional independent effect of Time 2 theory of mind on Time 3 ML nominations.
We next evaluated our hypothesized indirect (mediated) path- ways, using 1,000 bootstrap samples to estimate confidence inter- vals; for the purpose of these analyses, we accounted for the direct effects of the initial variable on the outcome variable even when they were nonsignificant. First, the indirect effect of Time 1 theory of mind on Time 3 LL nominations, mediated by Time 2 prosocial
Time 1
Time 2
Time 3
THEORY OF MIND AND PEER RELATIONS
263
     Prosocial Behaviour
.31**
.30**
.31**
-.30**
.32**
.20+
.34**
-34***
Prosocial Behaviour
Prosocial Behaviour
       Theory of Mind
Theory of Mind
Theory of Mind
   Figure 1.
Model showing autoregressive and cross-lagged effects of theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and
LL Nominations
least-like (LL) mominations over the three time points (error terms and verbal ability are not shown). 􏰆2(34,
N 􏰀 70) 􏰀 36.72, p 􏰀 .344, comparative fit index 􏰀 .982, root-mean-square error of approximation 􏰀 .034,
􏰁 􏰛􏰛 􏰛􏰛􏰛 standardized root-mean-square residual 􏰀 .063. p 􏰅 .10. p 􏰅 .01. p 􏰅 .001.
.48***
LL Nominations
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

264
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
Time 1
Time 2
Time 3
     Prosocial Behaviour
Prosocial Behaviour
Prosocial Behaviour
  .32**
.32**
.31*
.32**
.23*
.34**
.23*
     Theory of Mind
Theory of Mind
most-like (ML) nominations over the three time points (error terms and verbal ability are not shown). 􏰆2(34,
N 􏰀 70) 􏰀 37.20, p 􏰀 .324, comparative fit index 􏰀 .968, root-mean-square error of approximation 􏰀 .037,
standardized root-mean-square residual 􏰀 .067. p 􏰅 .05. p 􏰅 .01. p 􏰅 .001.
behavior, was found to be significant (standardized indirect effect, z 􏰀 􏰃.12, p 􏰅 .01). Next, we also found a significant indirect effect of Time 1 theory of mind on Time 3 ML nominations, mediated by Time 2 prosocial behavior (standardized indirect effect, z 􏰀 .094, p 􏰅 .05).
Moreover, an examination of modification indices of both mod- els showed that adding any further cross-lagged paths would not significantly improve model fit. Finally, in order to assess whether the cross-lagged paths were moderated by gender, we evaluated the two final models before and after forcing all cross-lagged path coefficients to be equal for boys and girls, and there was no significant deterioration in fit (for the model predicting LL nom- inations, 􏰇􏰆2(4) 􏰀 2.26, p 􏰄 .10; for the model predicting ML nominations, 􏰇􏰆2(4) 􏰀 2.56, p 􏰄 .10).
Discussion
Our results shed light on the sociocognitive and behavioral predictors of children’s peer relationships across the transition to school. First, the analyses revealed that individual differences in children’s early theory of mind significantly predict later prosocial behavior. In addition, children’s prosocial behavior at age 6 sig- nificantly predict later peer relationships. Thus, children who showed higher prosocial behavior in the first year of primary school were more likely to be accepted (and less rejected) by their classmates 1 year later. Furthermore, cross-lagged analyses re- vealed that prosocial behavior mediates the relationship between theory of mind and peer rejection and that prosocial behavior and theory of mind both contribute to predicting peer acceptance.
Linking Theory of Mind and Peer Relations
A major accomplishment of our longitudinal study is that we have been able to establish associations over 3 years between theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and peer relationships. First, our study confirmed the stability of individual differences in the level of theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and peer nominations (both positive and negative) across time. Specifically, rather than seeing development in terms of random fluctuations in task per- formance over time, our findings add to previous studies showing enduring patterns of individual differences in theory of mind (e.g., Lecce, Zocchi, Pagnin, Palladino, & Taumoepeau, 2010), proso-
cial behavior (e.g., Ensor, Spencer, & Hughes, 2011), and peer nominations (e.g., Ladd, Birch, & Buhs, 1999), and extend the present literature proving that these individual differences are stable over a 2-year period.
Crucially, even after controlling for this developmental stability, our results provided support for the mediational hypothesis about the indirect link between theory-of-mind skills and better peer relations, via higher levels of prosocial behavior. First, our anal- yses revealed a longitudinal link between early theory-of-mind skills and peer acceptance/rejection 2 years later. As noted earlier, Dockett (1997) found that a significant amount of the variability in peer popularity among preschoolers was explained by theory of mind, suggesting that being popular may somehow be linked to having a greater social sensitivity involving superior mind reading abilities. Our study also adds to other evidence that mindreading abilities are—at least sometimes—linked with individual differ- ences in the success of peer relations (e.g., Badenes et al., 2000; Banerjee et al., in press; Cassidy, Werner, Rourke, Zubernis, & Balaraman, 2003; Peterson & Siegal, 2002; Slaughter et al., 2002). However, our study stemmed from evidence of inconsistencies within that same literature suggesting that links between social understanding and interpersonal relations could not always be found. The present study takes us forward by identifying a crucial mediating construct that helps us to understand the mechanism by which theory of mind could exert an influence on social relation- ships.
As hypothesized, we found that a key proximal consequence of theory of mind was prosocial behavior and that the influence of theory of mind on peer nominations was, to a significant extent, dependent on the translation of theory of mind into socially coop- erative and helpful behaviors toward others. Specifically, we found a robust association between children’s sociocognitive understand- ing measured during preschool and first year of primary school and their prosocial behavior as rated by their school teachers 1 year later. This association between early psychological understanding and later behavioral outcomes is quite consolidated in the existing literature. Theorists have suggested that a prerequisite of respond- ing sensitively to others’ needs includes the ability to understand and infer emotions as well as the “cognitive act of imagining oneself in another’s place” (Hoffman, 1982, p. 284). Indeed, existing research conducted on a wide range of populations sug-
􏰛 􏰛􏰛 􏰛􏰛􏰛
.25*
.51***
Theory of Mind
   Figure 2.
Model showing autoregressive and cross-lagged effects of theory of mind, prosocial behavior, and
ML Nominations
ML Nominations
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

gests that the ability to recognize and interpret emotion cues, to engage in affective perspective taking, and to understand false belief may all contribute to specific positive social behaviors that can be evident in both family and classroom contexts (e.g., Cassidy et al., 2003; Denham et al., 1990; Eisenberg & Mussen, 1989; Izard et al., 2001; Lalonde & Chandler, 1995; Watson, Nixon, Wilson, & Capage, 1999).
Our results not only reinforce this message about the socially adaptive value of sociocognitive achievements but also demon- strate that this functionality is stable across development. Indeed, we found not only that theory of mind at age 5 predicts prosocial behavior at age 6 but also that theory of mind at age 6 predicts prosocial behavior at age 7. Most importantly, our modeling of the data leads us to the conclusion that these effects play a large role in promoting more positive (and less negative) relations with peers. As stressed by Strayer (1980) and by Eisenberg, Cameron, Tryon, and Dodez (1981), when children use their social skills in interacting with others, a kind of reciprocity in prosocial acts takes place, and such reciprocity facilitates children’s social life. Such a view is confirmed by other studies in which a relation between children’s prosocial behavior and peer nominations have been reported (Bukowski & Newcomb, 1984; Dekovic ́ & Gerris, 1994; Denham et al., 1990; Newcomb, Bukowski, & Pattee, 1993). Thus, a given child’s progress in theory of mind can help us explain subsequent transformations in his or her interpersonal relation- ships, but this depends on the extent to which the social under- standing is manifested in prosocial behavior.
Notwithstanding the support in our data for the overall media- tional hypothesis, our study found that the effects of theory of mind and prosocial behavior on peer relations were somewhat differentiated according to whether we focused on positive (ML) peer nominations or on negative (LL) nominations. This issue arises from several considerations. First, the correlation coefficient of the link between prosocial behavior at age 6 and peer nomina- tions at age 7 is higher for negative rather than positive nomina- tions. Second, the predictive relationship between prosocial behav- ior and peer acceptance is significant between age 6 and 7, whereas the predictive relationship between prosocial behavior and peer rejection is significant not only between age 6 and 7 but also between age 5 and 6. Finally, whereas the effect of early theory of mind on later peer rejection was mediated by prosocial behavior, the mediating role of prosocial behavior on later peer acceptance was accompanied by an independent contribution of theory of mind.
These results pose interesting questions about the different interpersonal consequences that might conceivably arise from hav- ing good theory-of-mind abilities. When it comes to predicting active rejection within a peer group, the role of prosocial behavior appears to be consistently and highly significant: Prosocial behav- iors at school with one’s peers and, in turn, the positive interac- tions that arise from such behaviors, significantly reduce the risk of been socially rejected. In other words, children seem to be partic- ularly sensitive to the lack of positive social behaviors, such as helping, cooperating, and sharing materials and toys, from an early age (Bigelow, 1977; Damon, 1988). Thus, although further work still needs to account for the additional importance of high anti- social behavior in bringing about active rejection from peers (see Coie, Dodge, & Kupersmidt, 1990; Keane & Calkins, 2004), our study suggests that prosocial behaviors resulting from good
theory-of-mind skills may be crucial for protecting the child from dislike, exclusion, and ostracism from the peer group.
In contrast, prosocial behavior is clearly not the only route from theory of mind to peer acceptance: In order to be chosen as “favorite classmates,” children might need to show the possession of multiple skills simultaneously. Although prosocial behavior undoubtedly promotes greater peer acceptance, theory of mind might also encourage positive relationships by diminishing behav- ior problems and by propelling a wide range of potential skills relating to the quality of conversations (Ensor & Hughes, 2008), conflict resolution strategies (J. Dunn & Herrera, 1997), and ef- fective participation in group activities (Flavell, Green, & Flavell, 1995). Further longitudinal research is clearly needed to establish these additional mediators of the association between theory of mind and peer acceptance.
Placing Social-Cognitive Development Within Social Context
Recent theoretical integrations of research findings have sug- gested that we need to understand the construction of social understanding within the context of social interaction (e.g., As- tington, 2003; J. Dunn, 1996). These approaches, which can be captured within a broad socioconstructivist framework (Carpen- dale & Lewis, 2004), raise important empirical questions about the role of social interactions (e.g., with parents, siblings, peers, and teachers) in the development of social cognition. Moreover, and perhaps even more interestingly, adopting such a perspective en- courages us to consider how the understanding of other people’s minds can be used to build stable and positive social relationships. This last issue deserves more attention in future research as, we believe, adopting a theory-of-mind-used-in-context perspective has pragmatic and theoretical implications for models of social- cognitive development. Indeed, such a view does not imply that having a better understanding of mind would necessarily result in positive outcomes. On the contrary, as discussed in more detail below, the quantity of mind reading per se may have little to do with how this knowledge will be used in social interactions; the latter clearly depends on a number of additional variables.
In the present study, we focused specifically on developmental processes that occur over the transition to school, which poses new and important demands for well-regulated behavior both inside and outside the classroom (see Campbell & von Stauffenberg, 2008; Kellam et al., 1994). An intriguing feature of our results is that although theory of mind had longitudinal effects on subse- quent prosocial behavior and peer nominations, it was not consis- tently connected to prosocial behavior or peer nominations within time points. This finding fits with the idea that theory of mind favors the development of behavioral and cognitive abilities (Lecce, Caputi, & Hughes, 2011), and particularly with the notion that time and experience are needed for children to capitalize on the sociocognitive skills and knowledge that they have acquired (Hughes, 2011). Indeed, other studies have reported distal effects of individual differences in theory of mind on a range of other outcomes such as sensitivity to teacher criticism (Cutting & Dunn, 2002; Lecce et al., 2011), academic achievement (Lecce, Caputi, Pagnin, & Banerjee, 2011), and metacognition (Lecce et al., 2010). Together, these studies testify to the salience of theory of mind in
THEORY OF MIND AND PEER RELATIONS
265
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

266
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
explaining later skills or attitudes and encourage researchers to take a dynamic perspective in developmental psychology.
Our findings suggest that the early years of primary school life may be a particularly important period for the manifestation of sociocognitive skills in real-life peer contexts. Indeed, as noted earlier, some previous studies have suggested that even though core developments in theory of mind occur during the preschool period (e.g., acquiring false belief; Wellman et al., 2001), many of the links between social understanding and peer relations may emerge later or become stronger in childhood, after the age of 5 years (e.g., Banerjee et al., in press; Dekovic ́ & Gerris, 1994; Slaughter et al., 2002). This may be the case for at least two reasons. On the one hand, the development of new cognitive abilities simply may not have immediate consequences for behav- ior (i.e., use may lag behind understanding; Hughes, 2011). On the other hand, there are good social-contextual reasons for expecting this pattern: Entry into primary school has long been regarded as a key social-developmental transition that requires children to manage interactions with a wide range of social partners in a much more independent and self-organized way than in the preschool years (see Higgins & Parsons, 1983). Future research may be able to tease apart these possibilities by examining the longitudinal effects of theory of mind on social behavior in different countries where the transition to school occurs in different ways and at different ages, and by examining the developmental trajectories among samples of children from a wider age range (see further comments in Lecce & Hughes, 2010).
This issue raises a further question about whether and precisely how theory-of-mind skills come to be reflected in everyday be- havior. As previously mentioned, simply possessing an under- standing of others’ mental states does not necessarily imply that this understanding will be used in social interactions or that it will be used for positive social purposes. Indeed a growing number of studies shows that a sophisticated theory of mind may facilitate self-reports of negative school experience (J. Dunn, 1995), efforts to deceive, manipulate and bully others (Arsenio & Lemerise, 2001; Astington, 2003; Gini, 2006; Sutton, Smith, & Swettenham, 1999), or in other words to achieve the goals of a “nasty mind” (Happe ́ & Frith, 1996). In line with this view, the associations between theory of mind and subsequent peer relationships, rather than being direct, appear to be mediated in the present study by prosocial behavior. However, it is important to note that the association between mind reading and prosocial behavior in the present study was moderate in size. One interpretation of the data is that superior theory-of-mind skills may be an important platform for prosocial behavior (which in turn would promote positive peer relations), but may not in themselves guarantee such an outcome. In addition, it is likely that the association between theory of mind and social outcomes may also be moderated by other factors such as temperamental characteristics, social information processing, motivational biases, age, and the identity of the social partner (e.g., familiar vs. unfamiliar peer). In fact, Renouf and colleagues (2010) have recently shown that among children with average or low levels of prosocial behavior, theory-of-mind skills can in fact promote higher levels of indirect or relational aggression toward others. Thus, combining the results from research on social cog- nition with insights gained from studies of social goals in school children (e.g., Wentzel, Barry, & Caldwell, 2004) may be a par-
ticularly fruitful approach to understanding when and for whom theory of mind leads to certain social outcomes.
A related question concerns how and to what extent experiences of using prosocial behavior (and having positive relationships as a result) come to have reciprocal influences on the development of social cognition. In the present study, we did not find that either prosocial behavior or peer nominations could predict improve- ments in theory of mind, but some other studies have shown that causal links between early social relationships and later sociocog- nitive understanding may in fact exist. For example, numerous studies on young children have considered the way in which aspects of the mother–child relationship, and particularly dimen- sions such as the use of mental-state language during conversa- tions (J. Dunn, Brown, & Beardsall, 1991), picture description (Ruffman, Slade, & Crowe, 2002), picture-book reading (Adria ́n, Clemente, & Villanueva, 2007), and free play (Meins et al., 2002), may have a causal role in promoting greater theory-of-mind skills. Most recently, Banerjee and colleagues (in press) have shown that peer rejection appears to predict subsequently poorer understand- ing of unintentional insults. The absence of this causal influence in the present study suggests that the impact of positive versus negative social relations on social understanding may depend crucially on the timescale for the development of that social understanding and/or the particular aspects of social understanding being measured. For example, it is possible that many of the features of theory of mind assessed in the present study could actually have been influenced by early familial experiences. Fur- thermore, the social-cognitive consequences of individual differ- ences in peer relations may only be evident when using specific, “naturalistic” measures of social understanding such as faux pas.
Limitations and Conclusions
A number of limitations in the present study must be recognized. The first, and perhaps more obvious, limitation concerns the sam- ple size. Having an in-depth 3-year longitudinal investigation of social-cognitive development among 70 young children is itself an important achievement, and the fact that our mediational hypoth- esis was found to be corroborated by the data testifies to the salience of these effects during the transition to school. Nonethe- less, having a bigger sample size would clearly increase the sta- tistical power and could therefore reveal relationships that did not emerge as significant in the present study. For example, it is entirely plausible that early prosocial behavior and peer relation- ships could affect children’s subsequent theory-of-mind reasoning, as has recently been found in older children (Banerjee et al., in press). In addition, having a bigger sample size would allow a more robust investigation of the role played by possible modera- tors, such as gender, in the proposed model, as well as the oppor- tunity to consider not only individual differences in continuous scores on the acceptance and rejection dimensions but also group differences between sociometric status categories (e.g., Coie et al., 1982).
A second area of limitation concerns the measurement of our core constructs. Although the combination of a wide range of tasks assessing the understanding of mental states provides us with confidence about having a comprehensive and age-appropriate measures of social comprehension at each time point, it may be the case that qualitatively distinct features of particular facets of social
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

understanding (e.g., appreciating mixed emotions vs. understand- ing double-bluffs) will have divergent relations with interpersonal functioning. Along the same lines, teachers’ ratings of prosocial behavior and simple ML and LL peer nominations can only give us a partial and rather undifferentiated picture of children’s social lives at school. In addition, the evaluations by teachers may have inflated results because they tend to show particularly strong associations with children’s cognitive characteristics. Adding ob- servational data would certainly help to draw a clearer picture (Denham, 1986; Pepler & Craig, 1998), although it is important to note that teachers are known to be reliable observers of children’s social behavior and that previous studies have found significant agreement between questionnaire and observational measures of children’s prosocial behavior (Cassidy et al., 2003; Rydell, Hagekull, & Bohlin, 1997); indeed, in this study, we found that teachers’ ratings were significantly correlated with peer nomina- tions. Nonetheless, a careful multi-informant assessment not only of general peer liking but also of dyadic friendship processes and reputational features (e.g., Parker & Asher, 1993; Zeller, Vannatta, Schafer, & Noll, 2003) would help us to draw a more refined portrait of children’s peer relations.
Finally, it is also worth noting another limitation of our mea- surement approach, this time relating to verbal ability. This was measured using a receptive vocabulary task at Times 1 and 2 and a grammar task at Time 3. As suggested by Ruffman, Slade, Rowlandson, Rumsey, and Garnham (2003), the latter task (TROG) not only evaluates syntactic ability but also requires semantic ability to comprehend the words used in syntax tests. Therefore, it can be considered as a more stringent test of verbal ability. In fact, neither the Time 2 nor the Time 3 measure had a significant independent association with theory of mind. However, we recognize that the change in measure makes longitudinal anal- yses much more difficult to interpret and leaves open the issue of replicability of our results.
Notwithstanding the limitations presented above, this study ex- tends our knowledge of the links between social understanding and interpersonal relations among children. In view of the fact that poor peer relations during childhood are implicated in the etiology of later deviance (Hoglund, Lalonde, & Leadbeater, 2008), our study may provide an impetus to the efforts of researchers and practitioners focusing on intervention and training to enhance theory-of-mind skills and thereby promote more positive social behaviors and peer relationships (Kloo & Perner, 2008).
References
Adria ́n, J. E., Clemente, R. A., & Villanueva, L. (2007). Mothers’ use of cognitive state verbs in picture-book reading and the development of children’s understanding of mind: A longitudinal study. Child Develop- ment, 78, 1052–1067. doi:10.1111/j.1467-8624.2007.01052.x
Arsenio, W., & Lemerise, E. A. (2001). Varieties of childhood bullying: Values, emotion processes, and social competence. Social Development, 10, 59–73. doi:10.1111/1467-9507.00148
Astington, J. (1993). The child’s discovery of the mind. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.
Astington, J. (2003). Sometimes necessary, never sufficient: False belief understanding and social competence. In B. Repacholi & V. Slaughter (Eds.), Individual differences in theory of mind: Implications for typical and atypical development (pp. 13–38). New York, NY: Psychology Press.
Astington, J. W., & Olson, D. R. (1995). The cognitive revolution in children’s understanding of mind. Human Development, 38, 179–189. doi:10.1159/000278313
Badenes, L., Estevan, R., & Bacete, F. (2000). Theory of mind and peer rejection at school. Social Development, 9, 271–283. doi:10.1111/1467- 9507.00125
Banerjee, R. (2004). The role of social experience in advanced social understanding. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 27, 97–98. doi:10.1017/ S0140525X04230035
Banerjee, R., & Watling, D. (2005). Children’s understanding of faux pas: Associations with peer relations. Hellenic Journal of Psychology, 2, 27–45. Retrieved from http://digirep.rhul.ac.uk/items/5d214aaf-a37b- 2873-d043– c11b972ac3d0/1/Banerjee_&_Watling_’05.pdf
Banerjee, R., Watling, D., & Caputi, M. (in press). Peer relations and the understanding of faux pas: Longitudinal evidence for bidirectional as- sociations. Child Development.
Baron-Cohen, S., Jolliffe, T., Mortimore, C., & Robertson, M. (1997). Another advanced test of theory of mind: Evidence from very high functioning adults with autism or Asperger Syndrome. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 38, 813–822. Retrieved from http:// autismresearchcentre.com/docs/papers/1997_BCetal_Anotheradvanced- test.pdf doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01599.x
Bentler, P. M. (1990). Comparative fit indexes in structural models. Psy- chological Bulletin, 107, 238–246. Retrieved from http://www.science- direct.com/science/journal/00332909. doi:10.1037/0033-2909.107.2.238
Bigelow, B. J. (1977). Children’s friendship expectations: A cognitive developmental study. Child Development, 48, 246–253. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/1128905. doi:10.2307/1128905
Bishop, D. V. M. (1982). Test for reception of grammar. Oxford, England: Oxford University Press.
Brown, J., Donelan-McCall, N., & Dunn, J. (1996). Why talk about mental states? The significance of children’s conversations with friends, sib- lings, and mothers. Child Development, 67, 836–849. doi:10.2307/ 1131864
Bukowski, W., & Newcomb, A. (1984). Stability and determinants of sociometric status and friendship choice: A longitudinal perspective. Developmental Psychology, 20, 941–952. doi:10.1037/0012- 1649.20.5.941
Bukowski, W. M. Sippola, L., Hoza, B., & Newcomb, A. F. (2000). Pages from a sociometric notebook: An analysis of nomination and rating scale measures of acceptance, rejections, and social preference. In A. H. Cillessen & W. M. Bukowski (Eds.), Recent advances in the measure- ment of acceptance and rejection in the peer system (pp. 11–26). San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass.
Campbell, S. B., & von Stauffenberg, C. (2008). Child characteristics and family processes that predict behavioral readiness for school. In A. Crouter & A. Booth (Eds.), Early disparities in school readiness: How families contribute to transitions into school (pp. 225–258). Mahwah, NJ: Erlbaum.
Carpendale, J. I., & Lewis, C. (2004). Constructing an understanding of mind: The development of children’s social understanding within social interaction. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 27, 79–96. doi:10.1017/ S0140525X04000032
Cassidy, K. W., Werner, R. S., Rourke, M., Zubernis, L. S., & Balaraman, G. (2003). The relationship between psychological understanding and positive social behaviors. Social Development, 12, 198–221. doi: 10.1111/1467-9507.00229
Coie, J. D., Dodge, K. A., & Coppotelli, H. (1982). Dimensions and types of social status: A cross-age perspective. Developmental Psychology, 18, 557–570. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.18.4.557
Coie, J. D., Dodge, K. A., & Kupersmidt, J. B. (1990). Peer group behavior and social status. In S. R. Asher & J. D. Coie (Eds.), Peer rejection in childhood (pp. 17–59). New York. NY: Cambridge University Press.
Cutting, A., & Dunn, J. (1999). Theory of mind, emotion understanding,
THEORY OF MIND AND PEER RELATIONS
267
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

268
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
language, and family background: Individual differences and interrela-
tions. Child Development, 70, 853– 865. doi:10.1111/1467-8624.00061 Cutting, A. L., & Dunn, J. (2002). The cost of understanding other people: Social cognition predicts young children’s sensitivity to criticism. Jour- nal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 43, 849 – 860. doi:10.1111/
1469-7610.t01–1-00047
Damon, W. (1988). The moral child. New York, NY: Free Press. Dekovic ́, M., & Gerris, J. R. M. (1994). Developmental analysis of social,
cognitive and behavioral differences between popular and rejected chil- dren. Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology, 15, 367–386. doi: 10.1016/0193-3973(94)90038-8
Denham, S. A. (1986). Social cognition, prosocial behavior, and emotion in preschoolers: Contextual validation. Child Development, 57, 194–201. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/1130651. doi:10.2307/ 1130651
Denham,S.A.(2006).Social–emotionalcompetenceassupportforschool readiness: What is it and how do we assess it? Early Education and Development, 17, 57–89. doi:10.1207/s15566935eed1701_4
Denham, S. A., McKinley, M., Couchoud, E. A., & Holt, R. (1990). Emotional and behavioral predictors of preschool peer ratings. Child Development, 61, 1145–1152. doi:10.2307/1130882
Dockett, S. (1997, April). Young children’s peer popularity and theories of mind. Poster presentation at the biennial meeting of the Society for Research in Child Development, Washington, DC.
Dunn, J. (1995). Children as psychologists: The later correlates of individ- ual differences in understanding of emotions and other minds. Cognition & Emotion, 9, 187–201. doi:10.1080/02699939508409008
Dunn, J. (1996). Family conversations and the development of social understanding. In B. Bernstein & J. Brannen (Eds.), Children, research and policy: Essays for Barbara Tizard (pp. 81–95). London, England: Taylor & Francis.
Dunn, J., Brown, J., & Beardsall, L. (1991). Family talk about feeling states and children’s later understanding of others’ emotions. Developmental Psychology, 27, 448–455. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.27.3.448
Dunn, J., Brown, J., Slomkowski, C., Tesla, C., & Youngblade, L. (1991). Young children’s understanding of other people’s feelings and beliefs: Individual differences and their antecedents. Child Development, 62, 1352–1366. doi:10.2307/1130811
Dunn, J., & Cutting, A. (1999). Understanding others, and individual differences in friendship interactions in young children. Social Devel- opment, 8, 201–219. doi:10.1111/1467-9507.00091
Dunn, J., Cutting, A. L., & Fisher, N. (2002). Old friends, new friends: Predictors of children’s perspective on their friends at school. Child Development, 73, 621–635. doi:10.1111/1467-8624.00427
Dunn, J., & Herrera, C. (1997). Conflict resolution with friends, siblings, and mothers: A developmental perspective. Aggressive Behavior, 23, 343–357. doi:10.1002/(SICI)1098-2337(1997)23:5􏰅343::AID-AB4􏰄 3.0.CO;2-J
Dunn, L. M., & Dunn, L. M. (1981). Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test- Revised. Circle Pines, MN: American Guidance Service.
Eisenberg, N., Cameron, E., Tryon, K., & Dodez, R. (1981). Socialization of prosocial behavior in the classroom. Developmental Psychology, 17, 773–782. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.17.6.773
Eisenberg, N., & Mussen, P. H. (1989). The roots of prosocial behavior in children. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press. doi: 10.1017/CBO9780511571121
Ensor, R., & Hughes, C. (2008). Content or connectedness? Mother–child talk and early social understanding. Child Development, 79, 201–216. doi:10.1111/j.1467-8624.2007.01120.x
Ensor, R., Spencer, D., & Hughes, C. (2011). ‘You feel sad?’ Emotion understanding mediates effects of verbal ability and mother–child mu- tuality on prosocial behaviors: Findings from 2 years to 4 years. Social Development, 20, 3–110. doi:10.1111/j.1467-9507.2009.00572.x
Flavell, J. H. (2004). Theory-of-mind development: Retrospect and pros-
pect. Merrill-Palmer Quarterly, 50, 274 –290. doi:10.1353/
mpq.2004.0018
Flavell, J. H., Green, F. L., & Flavell, E. R. (1995). Young children’s
knowledge about thinking. Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development, 60, 1–96. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/ stable/1166124. doi:10.2307/1166124
Garner, P. W., Curenton, S. M., & Taylor, K. (2005). Predictors of mental state understanding in preschoolers of varying socioeconomic back- grounds. International Journal of Behavioral Development, 29, 271– 281. doi:10.1177/01650250544000053
Gini, G. (2006). Social cognition and moral cognition in bullying: What’s wrong? Aggressive Behavior, 32, 528–539. doi:10.1002/ab.20153
Goodman, R. (1997). The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: A research note. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 38, 581– 586. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x
Gordis,F.W.,Rosen,A.B.,&Grand,S.(1989,April).Youngchildren’s understanding of simultaneous conflicting emotions. Paper presented at the biennial meeting of the Society for Research in Child Development. Kansas City, MO.
Gresham, F. M., & Elliott, S. N. (1990). The social skills rating system: Examiner’s manual. Circle Pines, MN: American Guidance Services. Happe ́, F. (1994). An advanced test of theory of mind: Understanding of
story characters’ thoughts and feeling by able autistic, mentally handi- capped and normal children and adults. Journal of Autism and Devel- opmental Disorders, 24, 129–154. doi:10.1007/BF02172093
Happe ́, F., & Frith, U. (1996). Theory of mind and social impairment in children with conduct disorder. British Journal of Developmental Psy- chology, 14, 385–398. Retrieved from http://www.bpsjournals.co.uk/ journals/bjdp/ doi:10.1111/j.2044-835X.1996.tb00713.x
Harris, P. L., Johnson, C., Hutton, D., Andrews, G., & Cooke, T. (1989). Young children’s theory of mind and emotion. Cognition & Emotion, 3, 379–400. doi:10.1080/02699938908412713
Higgins, E. T., & Parsons, J. E. (1983). Social cognition and the social life of the child: Stages as subcultures. In E. T. Higgins, D. N. Ruble, & W. W. Hartup (Eds.), Social cognition and social development: A sociocultural perspective (pp. 15– 62). Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.
Hoffman, M. (1982). Development of prosocial motivation: Empathy and guilt. In N. Eisenberg (Ed.), The development of prosocial behavior (pp. 281–313). New York, NY: Academic Press.
Hoglund, W. L. G., Lalonde, C. E., & Leadbeater, B. J. (2008). Social- cognitive competence, peer rejection and neglect, and behavioral and emotional problems in middle childhood. Social Development, 17, 528 – 553. doi:10.1111/j.1467-9507.2007.00449.x
Hollingshead, A. B. (1975). Four factor index of social status. New Haven, CT: Yale University.
Hu, L. T., & Bentler, P. M. (1998). Fit indices in covariance structure modeling: Sensitivity to underparameterized model misspecification. Psychological Methods, 3, 424–453. Retrieved from http://www .sciencedirect.com/science/journal/1082989X doi:10.1037/1082- 989X.3.4.424
Hu, L. T., & Bentler, P. M. (1999). Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alterna- tives. Structural Equation Modeling, 6, 1–55. doi:10.1080/ 10705519909540118
Hughes, C. (2011). Social understanding and social lives. From toddler- hood through to the transition to school. Hove, UK: Psychology Press. Hughes, C., Adlam, A., Happe ́, F., Jackson, J., Taylor, A., & Caspi, A. (2000). Good test-retest reliability for standard and advanced false-belief tasks across a wide range of abilities. Journal of Child Psychology and
Psychiatry, 41, 483–490. doi:10.1111/1469-7610.00633
Hughes, C., & Dunn, J. (1997). “Pretend you didn’t know”: Preschoolers’ talk about mental states in pretend play. Cognitive Development, 12,
477–499. doi:10.1016/S0885-2014(97)90019-8
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

Hughes, C., Ensor, R. A., Allen, L. L., Devine, R. T., De Rosnay, M., Koyasu, M., . . . Lecce, S. (2011, March). Theory of mind performance in British, Australian, Japanese and Italian children: Contrasts in cul- ture or age of school entry? Paper presented at the Society for Research in Child Development (SRCD) Biennial Conference, Montreal, Canada.
Hughes, C., Fujisawa, K., Ensor, R., Lecce, S., & Marfleet, R. (2006). Cooperation and conversations about the mind: A study of individual differences in two-year-olds and their siblings. British Journal of De- velopmental Psychology, 24, 53–72. doi:10.1348/026151005X82893
Hughes, C., & Leekam, S. (2004). What are the links between theory of mind and social relations? Review, reflections and new directions for studies of typical and atypical development. Social Development, 13, 590–619. doi:10.1111/j.1467-9507.2004.00285.x
Izard, C. E., Fine, S. E., Schultz, D., Mostow, A. J., Ackerman, B. P., & Youngstrom, E. (2001). Emotion knowledge as a predictor of social behavior and academic competence in children at risk. Psychological Science, 12, 18–23. doi:10.1111/1467-9280.00304
Keane, S. P., & Calkins, S. D. (2004). Predicting kindergarten peer social status from toddler and preschool problem behavior. Journal of Abnor- mal Child Psychology, 32, 409 – 423. doi:10.1023/B: JACP.0000030294.11443.41
Kellam, S. G., Rebok, G. W., Ialongo, N. S., & Mayer, L. S. (1994). The course and malleability of aggressive behavior from early first grade into middle school: Results of a developmental epidemiology-based preven- tive trial. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry and Allied Dis- ciplines, 35, 259–281. doi:10.1111/j.1469-7610.1994.tb01161.x
Kloo, D., & Perner, J. (2008). Training theory of mind and executive control: A tool for improving school achievement? Mind, Brain, and Education, 2, 122–127. doi:10.1111/j.1751-228X.2008.00042.x
Ladd, G. W. (1999). Peer relationships and social competence during early and middle childhood. Annual Review of Psychology, 50, 333–359. doi:10.1146/annurev.psych.50.1.333
Ladd, G. W., Birch, S. H., & Buhs, E. S. (1999). Children’s social and scholastic lives in kindergarten: Related spheres of influence? Child Development, 70, 1373–1400. doi:10.1111/1467-8624.00101
Ladd, G. W., & Profilet, S. M. (1996). The Child Behaviour Scale: A teacher-report measure of young children’s aggressive, withdrawn, and prosocial behaviors. Developmental Psychology, 32, 1008–1024. doi: 10.1037/0012-1649.32.6.1008
Lalonde, C. E., & Chandler, M. J. (1995). False belief understanding goes to school: On the social-emotional consequences of coming early or late to a first theory of mind. Cognition & Emotion, 9, 167–185. doi:10.1080/ 02699939508409007
Lecce, S., Caputi, M., & Hughes, C. (2011). Does sensitivity to criticism mediate the relationship between theory of mind and academic achieve- ment? Journal of Experimental Child Psychology, 110, 313–331. doi: 10.1016/j.jecp.2011.04.011
Lecce, S., Caputi, M., Pagnin, A., & Banerjee, R. (2011). Theory of mind and school achievement: The mediating role of peer relationships. Manuscript submitted for publication.
Lecce,S.,&Hughes,C.(2009,September).Theoryofmindandchildren’s social experiences and expectations: A cross cultural study. Paper pre- sented at the annual meeting of the British Psychological Society, Nottingham, UK.
Lecce, S., & Hughes, C. (2010). ‘The Italian job?’: Comparing theory of mind performance in British and Italian children. British Journal of Developmental Psychology, 28, 747–766. doi:10.1348/ 026151009X479006
Lecce, S., Zocchi, S., Pagnin, A., Palladino, P., & Taumoepeau, M. (2010). Reading minds: The relation between children’s mental state knowledge and their metaknowledge about reading. Child Development, 81, 1876 – 1893. doi:10.1111/j.1467-8624.2010.01516.x
Mashburn, A. J., & Pianta, R. C. (2006). Social relationships and school
readiness. Early Education and Development, 17, 151–176. doi:10.1207/
s15566935eed1701_7
McIntyre, L. L., Blacher, J., & Baker, B. L. (2006). Transition to school:
Adaptation in young children with and without developmental delays. Journal of Intellectual Disability Research, 50, 349–361. doi:10.1111/ j.1365-2788.2006.00783.x
Meins, E., Fernyhough, C., Wainwright, R., Gupta, M., Fradley, E., & Tuckey, M. (2002). Maternal mind-mindedness and attachment security as predictors of theory of mind understanding. Child Development, 73, 1715–1726. doi:10.1111/1467-8624.00501
Milligan, K., Astington, J., & Dack, L. A. (2007). Language and theory of mind: Meta-analysis of the relation between language ability and false- belief understanding. Child Development, 78, 622–646. doi:10.1111/ j.1467-8624.2007.01018.x
Nelson, D., & Crick, N. (1999). Rose-colored glasses: Examining the social information processing of prosocial young adolescents. Journal of Early Adolescence, 19, 17–38. doi:10.1177/0272431699019001002
Nelson, K. (1996). Language in cognitive development: The emergence of the mediated mind. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press. Newcomb, A. F., & Bukowski, W. M. (1983). Social impact and social
preference as determinants of children’s peer group status. Developmen-
tal Psychology, 19, 856–867. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.19.6.856 Newcomb, A. F., Bukowski, W. M., & Pattee, L. (1993). Children’s peer relations: A meta-analytic review of popular, rejected, neglected, con- troversial, and average sociometric status. Psychological Bulletin, 113, 99–128. Retrieved from http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/bul/ doi:
10.1037/0033-2909.113.1.99
Pakaslahti, L., Karjalainen, A., & Keltikangas-Jarvinen, L. (2002). Rela-
tionships between adolescent prosocial problem-solving strategies, prosocial behavior and social acceptance. International Journal of Be- havioral Development, 26, 137–144. doi:10.1080/01650250042000681
Parker, J. G., & Asher, S. R. (1993). Friendship and friendship quality in middle childhood: Links with peer group acceptance and feelings of loneliness and social dissatisfaction. Development and Psychology, 29, 611–621. Retrieved from http://www.psych.utah.edu/classes/2007_fall/ 3220_001/readings/parker.pdf doi:10.1037/0012-1649.29.4.611
Parkhurst, J. T., & Asher, S. R. (1992). Peer rejection in middle school: Subgroup differences in behavior, loneliness, and interpersonal con- cerns. Developmental Psychology, 28, 231–241. Retrieved from http:// www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/00121649. doi:10.1037/0012- 1649.28.2.231
Pepler, D. J., & Craig, W. M. (1998). Assessing children’s peer relation- ships. Child and Adolescent Mental Health, 3, 176–182. doi:10.1111/ 1475-3588.00238
Peterson, C. C., Garnett, M., Kelly, A., & Attwood, T. (2009). Everyday social and conversation applications of theory-of-mind understanding by children with autism-spectrum disorders or typical development. Euro- pean Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 18, 105–115. doi:10.1007/ s00787-008-0711-y
Peterson, C. C., & Siegal, M. (2002). Mindreading and moral awareness in popular and rejected preschoolers. British Journal of Developmental Psychology, 20, 205–224. doi:10.1348/026151002166415
Pons, F., & Harris, P. L. (2000). Test of Emotion Comprehension-TEC. Oxford, England: Oxford University Press.
Pons, F., & Harris, P. L. (2002). Theory of Mind Test (TMT). Cambridge, England: Harvard University Press.
Putallaz, M. (1983). Predicting children’s sociometric status from their behavior. Child Development, 54, 1417–1426. Retrieved from http:// www.jstor.org/stable/1129804
Renouf, A., Brendgen, M., Parent, S., Vitaro, F., Zelazo, P., Boivin, M., . . . Se ́guin, J. R. (2010). Relations between theory of mind and indirect and physical aggression in kindergarten: Evidence of the moderating role of prosocial behaviors. Social Development, 19, 535–555. doi:10.1111/ j.1467-9507.2009.00552.x
THEORY OF MIND
AND PEER RELATIONS
269
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

270
CAPUTI, LECCE, PAGNIN, AND BANERJEE
Repacholi, B., & Slaughter, V. (Eds.). (2003). Individual differences in theory of mind: Implications for typical and atypical development. Hove, UK: Psychology Press.
Ruffman, T., Perner, J., & Parkin, L. (1999). How parenting style affects false belief understanding. Social Development, 8, 395–411. doi: 10.1111/1467-9507.00103
Ruffman, T., Slade, L., & Crowe, E. (2002). The relation between chil- dren’s and mothers’ mental state language and theory-of-mind under- standing. Child Development, 73, 734 –751. doi:10.1111/1467- 8624.00435
Ruffman, T., Slade, L., Rowlandson, K., Rumsey, C., & Garnham, A. (2003). How language relates to belief, desire, and emotion understand- ing. Cognitive Development, 18, 139–158.
Rydell, A., Hagekull, B., & Bohlin, G. (1997). Measurement of two social competence aspects in middle childhood. Developmental Psychology, 33, 824–833. Retrieved from http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/ journal/00121649. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.33.5.824
Slaughter, V., Dennis, M., & Pritchard, M. (2002). Theory of mind and peer acceptance in preschoolers. British Journal of Developmental Psy- chology, 20, 545–564. Retrieved from http://www2.psy.uq.edu.au/􏰈vps/ slaughterdennispritchard.pdf
Steiger, J. H. (1990). Structural model evaluation and modification: An interval estimation approach. Multivariate Behavioral Research, 25, 173–180. Retrieved from http://www.statpower.net/Steiger%20Biblio/ Steiger90b.pdf doi:10.1207/s15327906mbr2502_4
Strayer, J. (1980). A naturalistic study of empathic behaviors and their relation to affective states and perspective-taking skills in preschool children. Child Development, 51, 815–822. Retrieved from http:// www.jstor.org/stable/1129469
Sullivan, K., Zaitchik, D., & Tager-Flusberg, H. (1994). Preschoolers can attribute second-order beliefs. Developmental Psychology, 30, 395– 402. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.30.3.395
Sutton, J., Smith, P., & Swettenham, J. (1999). Social cognition and bullying: Social inadequacy or skilled manipulation? British Journal of Developmental Psychology, 17, 435–450. Retrieved from http:// www.bpsjournals.co.uk/journals/bjdp/ doi:10.1348/026151099165384
Tager-Flusberg, H. (2003). Exploring the relationship between theory of mind and social-communicative functioning in children with autism. In B. Repacholi & V. Slaughter (Eds.), Individual differences in theory of
mind: Implications for typical and atypical development (pp. 197–212).
Hove, UK: Psychology Press.
Watson, A. C., Nixon, C. L., Wilson, A., & Capage, L. (1999). Social
interaction skills and theory of mind in young children. Developmental Psychology, 35, 386–391. Retrieved from http://www.sciencedirect .com/science/journal/00121649. doi:10.1037/0012-1649.35.2.386
Weir, K., & Duveen, G. (1981). Further development and validation of the Prosocial Behaviour Questionnaire for use by teachers. Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 22, 357–374. doi:10.1111/j.1469- 7610.1981.tb00561.x
Wellman, H. M. (1990). The child’s theory of mind. London, England: MIT Press.
Wellman, H. M., Cross, D., & Watson, J. (2001). Meta-analysis of theory- of-mind development: The truth about false belief. Child Development, 72, 655–684. doi:10.1111/1467-8624.00304
Wentzel, K. R., Barry, C. M. N., & Caldwell, K. A. (2004). Friendships in middle school: Influences on motivation and school adjustment. Journal of Educational Psychology, 96, 195–203. Retrieved from http:// www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/00220663. doi:10.1037/0022- 0663.96.2.195
Wimmer, H., & Hartl, M. (1991). Against the Cartesian view on mind: Young children’s difficulty with own false beliefs. British Journal of Developmental Psychology, 9, 125–138. Retrieved from http:// onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)2044-835X doi: 10.1111/j.2044-835X.1991.tb00866.x
Wimmer, H., & Perner, J. (1983). Beliefs about beliefs: Representation and constraining function of wrong beliefs in young children’s understand- ing of deception. Cognition, 13, 103–128. doi:10.1016/0010- 0277(83)90004-5
Zeller, M., Vannatta, K., Schafer, J., & Noll, R. B. (2003). Behavioral reputation: A cross-age perspective. Developmental Psychology, 39, 129–139. Retrieved from http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/dev/ doi: 10.1037/0012-1649.39.1.129
Zerwas, S., Balaraman, G., & Brownell, C. (2004). Constructing an un- derstanding of mind with peers. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 27, 130–130. doi:10.1017/S0140525X04590039
Received October 14, 2010 Revision received May 23, 2011
Accepted June 9, 2011 􏰜
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.
