 DevelopmentalPsychology Copyright 1998bytheAmericanPsychologicalAssociation,Inc. 1998,Vol. 34, No. 5, 1026 1037 0012-1649198/$3,00
Understanding Mind and Emotion: Longitudinal AssociationsWith Mental-State Talk Between Young Friends
Claire Hughes and Judy Dunn Institute of Psychiatry
Developmentalchangesin children'sunderstandingof mind and emotionand their mental-statetalk in conversationswith friends wereexaminedin a longitudinal study of 50 children (M ageat each time point = 3 years 11 months, 4 years 6 months, 5 years 0 months). Significant and related improvementsovertime werefound for both theory-of-mind taskperformanceandaffectiveperspec- tive taking. Associatedwith thesecognitivedevelopmentswere quantitative and qualitative changes in children'sreferencesto mental statesin their conversationswith friends. Individual differencesin theory of mind, emotion understanding,and mental-statetalk were strikingly stable over the 13- month period. Although there were no gender differences in children's task performances,girls showedmorefrequentandmoredevelopedmental-statetalk thanboys.
Developmentalchangesin young children'sunderstandingof mental states have been researchedintensively in the past 15 y e a r s . D e s p i t e t h e n u m b e r o f s t u d i e s i n t h e f i e l d , v e r y f e w h a v e had a longitudinal developmentaldesign. As a result, little is known about the stability of individual differencesin children's mentalizing skills. Longitudinal studies are also neededto ex- plore relations betweendevelopmentaltrajectoriesin different domains. For example, understandingbelief and understanding emotion are linked conceptuallybut may show contrastingante- cedentsand sequelae(J. Dunn, 1995). Similarly, researchers have recently begun to explore genderdifferencesin children's e a r l y s o c i a l u n d e r s t a n d i n g ;h o w e v e r , i t i s n o t c l e a r w h e t h e r t h e s e differencescan be explainedby genderdifferencesin language development(Happ6, 1995) or in peerrelationships(Ruble & Martin, 1998). In this article, thesethree topics are addressed through a 1-year longitudinal study of 25 pairs of friends.
Stability of Individual Differences in Understanding Belief and Its Correlates
The ever-growing number of experimental studies of chil- dren's understandingof mind reflects a common consensusthat
ClaireHughes,Medical ResearchCouncilChild andAdolescentPsy- chiatry Unit, Institute of Psychiatry,London, England; Judy Dunn, So- cial, Geneticand DevelopmentalPsychiatry ResearchCentre, Institute of Psychiatry,London, England.
This work was conductedwith the support of National Institutes of HealthGrantHD 23158.Wethankall childrenandstaffatthefollowing South London and Kent nurseriesand schoolsfor their participation in the study: Crawford, Dulwich Village, Dulwich Wood, Grove, Heber, Langbourne,Mayfield, St.Alban's,St.Bartholomew's,St.Francis's,St. George's,St. Luke's, SumnerNursery, and Sunnyhill. We also thank FrancescaHapp6 and Tom O'Connor for their helpful commentson a previousversionof this article.
Correspondenceconcerningthis articleshouldbeaddressedto Claire Hughes, Medical ResearchCouncil Child and Adolescent Psychiatry Unit, Institute of Psychiatry, De CrespignyPark, London SE5 8AF, England.Electronicmail may be sentto clare.hughes@iop.bpmf.ac.uk.
understandingmental statesis essentialfor everydaysocial rela- tions. Yet surprisingly little is known about the real-life corre- l a t e s o f i n d i v i d u a l d i f f e r e n c e s i n c h i l d r e n ' s p e r f o r m a n c eo n t e s t s of mental-stateunderstanding. However, four recent observa- tional studies have shown a significant correlation between false-beliefperformanceand both the quality (Astington & Jen- kins, 1995; Taylor & Carlson, 1997) and quantity (Hughes & Dunn, 1997; Youngblade& Dunn, 1995) of children's pretend play with friends. Other observational studies have shown a correlation betweenfalse-belieftask performanceand both the connectednessof children's communication (Slomkowski & D u n n , 1 9 9 6 ) a n d t h e f r e q u e n c y a n d s o p h i s t i c a t i o n o f t h e i r t a l k about mental stateswith friends (Brown, Donelan-McCall, & Dunn, 1996; Hughes& Dunn, 1997).
Investigationssuchasthoseabovenot only suggestthat indi- vidual differencesin mental-stateawarenessare meaningful for children's social lives, but also demonstratethe utility of com- bining experimentaland observationalmethods.At the same time, theissueof externalvalidity appearsespeciallysalientin observationalstudies, becausesubtle changesof context have been associatedwith striking differences in talk and behavior (J. Dunn, Brown, & Beardsall, 1991; Gottman, 1986). These contrastssuggestthat laboratory-basedresearchin which chil- drenarecharacterizedastheory-of-mind"passers"or "failers" may be misleading.This issue is highlighted by a recent study indicating poor test-retest reliability for false-belief tasks (Mayes, Klin, Tercyak, Ciccetti, & Cohen, 1996). Examining the stability of individual differencesin false-belieftask perfor- mance(and its correlates)was thereforean important aim of thepresentstudy.Highly stabledifferencesbetweenchildren werepredicted,primarily on thebasisof findingsfrom anearly study by J. Dunn, Brown, Slomkowski, Tesla, and Youngblade (1991) in which family talk about feelings and cooperative interactions between siblings at 33 months were found to be related to children's social understanding7 months later.
Relations Between UnderstandingBelief and Emotion and Children's Mental-StateTalk
Studiesof children's understandingof emotionsindicate that individual differences are associatedwith differences in pro-
1026

 socialbehavior(Denham,McKinley, Conchoud,& Holt, 1990) and show some stability over time (Brown & Dunn, 1996). However,thesepatternsmay not generalizeto children'sunder- standing of mental states such as belief. For example, using a Pennsylvaniasampleof 40-month-oldchildren, J. Dunn (1995) found that individual differences in performance on tests of emotional perspectivetaking and false-beliefexplanation were unrelated. Indeed, at follow-up when the children were 6 years old, early understandingof emotions was related to positive perceptionof peerexperiencesw, hereasearly false-beliefunder- standing was related to negative initial perceptionsof school, greater sensitivity to teacher criticism, and harsher self-judg- ments of performance(J. Dunn, 1995). A secondaim of this study was to track children's developingunderstandingof emo- tion and belief to exploreDunn's hypothesisthat developments in each domain have differential sequelae.
A third aim of the study was to investigaterelationsbetween children's interactionswith friends and their developingunder- standingof mind. An alternativeand tempting interpretationof J. Dunn, Brown, Slomkowski, et al.'s (1991) findings of an associationbetweencooperativesibling interactionat 33 months and false-beliefperformanceat 40 months is that peer interac- tions have a facilitatory effect on sociocognitivedevelopment (see Hartup, 1996). That is, sibling interactionscould provide anenrichedcontextfor children'sleamingaboutothers'minds. Supportfor theassociationbetweensiblinginteractionandchil- dren's developingunderstandingof mind can be found in three recent independent studies. Pemer, Ruffman, and Leekam (1994) reported that children from large families showed an acceleratedrate of successon standardfalse-belieftasks. Jen- kins and Astington (1996) replicatedthis effect but found that the beneficial effect of siblings was only significant for verbally less-ablechildren. Finally, Lewis, Freeman,Kyriakidou, Mari- daki-Kassotaki, and Berridge (1996) found facilitatory effects of close contact with not only siblings but also membersof the extendedfamily. The conclusionfrom thesestudiesis that even if mentalizingability is innately specified(Leslie, 1987), chil- dren's social experiencesmay well play an important role in its development.
Another lesson to be learned from longitudinal researchis that theremay be important developmentalchangesin when and w h y c h i l d r e n t a l k a b o u t m e n t a l s t a t e s .F o r e x a m p l e , a t 3 3 m o n t h s of age,youngchildren'stalk aboutinnerstatesis predominantly with their mothers (and often in the context of disputes with siblings), whereas at 47 months of age, children show more frequentmental-statetalk with their siblings or friends, and this talk is often in the context of cooperativeplay (Brown et al., 1996). In itself, this developmentalshift is extremelyinteresting; the findings are also useful at a practical level, as they enable researchersto focus on specific contexts that are likely to be rich "seams" for investigatingchildren's conversationsabout mental states(e.g., Hughes & Dunn, 1997).
A focus on friends also provides a bridge betweencognitive p e r s p e c t i v e so n c h i l d r e n ' s d e v e l o p m e n ta n d t h e g r o w i n g b o d y o f socialresearchinto thedevelopmentalsignificanceof children's friendships. With the exceptionof Howes's (1988) studies of preschoolers,much of this work has been done with school-age children and adolescents.Yet forming friendships is a major social achievementfor preschool-agechildren, and one that may well be tied to their growing understandingof others' beliefs,
intentions, and desires. In addition, numerous studies have shown that conversationsbetweenfriends are more vigorous, mutually oriented,and elaboratedthan thosebetweennonfriends (Newcomb & Bagwell, 1995). For thesetwo reasons,conversa- tions between friends offer a privileged view on how young children apply their developingsociocognitiveskills to real-life interactionswith close others.
Gender Differences in Social Understandingand Mental-StateTalk
A final topic of interestin the presentstudy stemsfrom recent findings that suggest gender differences in cognitive and af- fective perspectivetaking (Brody, 1985; Happ6, 1995). One possibility is that the differencesbetweenboys' and girls' per- formanceson tests of understandingmind and emotion reflect genderdifferencesin languagedevelopment(e.g., Huttenlocher, Haight, Bryk, Seltzer,& Lyons, 1991). Altematively, thesedif- ferencesin socialunderstandingmay relateto differencesin the quality of boys' and girls' early social relationshipswith peers: Friendshipsbetweengirls may be more intimate and mutually oriented, and so lead to more rapid developmentin their under- standingof others.
Method
Participants
At the start of the study, 50 children (25 pairs of friends) from four localinner-citynurseryschoolswererecruited:25boysand25girls; 25 Caucasianchildren and 25 children of African or Caribbeanorigin. All children spoke English as their first languageat home. Participants in- cluded10boy-boypairs,10girl-girl pairs,and5boy-girlpairs,and rangedin agefrom 3 years3 monthsto 4 years7 months(M = 3 years 11 months, SD = 5 months). Pairs of friends were identified by class teachersand were included if also nominated by a secondmemberof staff. Themeanduration of thechildren'sfriendship prior to testing was 9months(range= 2monthsto3years).Friendsmeteverydayattheir nursery,andonaveragemet2-4 timesamonthoutsidethenursery.
As the children were followed up over the year,most of the group movedfrom nurseryto primary schools.Althoughmanypairs of friends were separatedby this transition to school, several friendship dyads continuedto play togetheroutsideschool,either becausethey lived very neareachotheror becausetheir motherswerefriends.As aresult, it was possible to film 19 (75%) of the original 25 friendship dyads at allthreetimepointsoverthecourseoftheyear,evenif 1or2ofthese film sessionstookplacein onefriend'shomeratherthanin thenursery. Theremaining6pairswerefilmedwithnewfriendsintheirnewschools. Although the new children recruitedto the study over the courseof the yearwereincludedin all thetestingsessions,for thesakeof simplicity thedatareportedherearerestrictedto resultsfrom theoriginal group of 50 children. All of thesechildren were seenat all three time points, so there was no dropout from the study.
Each of the four nurseriesused for initial recruitmentserveda pre- dominantly low-incomecatchmentarea.Parentaloccupationof partici- pants in this study reflectedthis distribution, although families ranged from thosein which both parentswereunemployed(8 cases)to those in which both parentswereprofessionally employed(7 cases).Fathers' occupationsfor theprevious2-yearsweresummarizedasfollows: unem- ployed(13);domesticworker(7);manualworker(7); cabdriver(5); clerical worker (5); accountant (8); teacher (1); engineer(3); and doctor( 1).
UNDERSTANDINGMIND
AND MENTAL-STATE TALK 1027

 1028
HUGHES AND DUNN
ExperimentalDesign
Theaimof thestudywasto observefriendshippairsandadminister a setof taskstappingchildren'sunderstandingof mind andemotionat three time points evenly spreadover a 1-year period. School holidays disruptedtheschedulingsomewhat,andsothedatawerein fact collected atintervalsof 7and13monthsfromthestartof thestudy.Themean ageof the group was 3 years 11 monthsat Time 1; 4 years6 months at Time 2; and5 yearsexactlyat Time 3 (SD= 4.7, 5.2, and4.9 months, respectively).
At eachtime point, friends were filmed for 20 min in dyadic play in a quiet room of the nurseryor school, equipped(by the experimenter) with a big box of toys anddressing-upmaterials( seeMaterialssection), and a cine-cameramountedon a tripod in one corner. One week later, children were testedindividually for their understandingof mind and e m o t i o n . U n d e r s t a n d i n go f m i n d w a s t e s t e d u s i n g t h r e e p a r a l l e l t a s k s e t s thatwerecounterbalancedacrosstimepointsandparticipants.At each timepoint,childrenweregiventwo standardfalse-beliefpredictiontasks, one emotion false-beliefprediction task, three false-beliefexplanation tasks, and two deception tasks. Understandingof emotion was tested using Denham's(1986) affective labeling and affective perspective- taking tasksat Times 1 and 2, and Gordis, Rosen,and Grand's(1989) mixed emotion task at Time 3. In addition, at Times 2 and 3 children wereinterviewedabouttheirreal-lifeunderstandingof causesof emotion for themselvesand close others. Their responsesat each time point were extremelysimilar (seeJ. Dunn & Hughes,1998), and so the data presentedherearefrom Time 2 only. Backgroundmeasuresof children's verbalandnonverbalabilitieswereobtainedatTime 1usingtheBritish Picture Vocabulary Scale (L. M. Dunn, Dunn, Whetton, & Pintilie, 1982) and all six performancesubtestsof the McCarthy Intelligence Scales(McCarthy, 1972).
Materials Dressing-Up Materials and Role-Play Toys
Items included one fireman's hat; one pirate hat, jacket, toy hook, and cutlass; one cowboy hat; one scary mask; one fairy mask; one crown; one ballet tutu; one toy handbagwith money, sunglassesa, nd jewels; two ragdollsandtwo SesameStreethandpuppetso; netoy police set with two hats, two Walkie-Talkie phones,two handcuffsand two badges;one toy doctor'scasewith stethoscopet,hermometer,otoscope, tendon-hammer,bandage,and syringe; one toy cookset with cooker, blender,pans,plates,cups,cutlery,andfood; onetoy toolboxwith multi- coloredtorch, spirit level, tape-measurep,liers, saw,andhammer.(At the secondand third time points, thesedressing-upmaterialswere renewed, althoughthe themesfor the toys were unchanged.)
TaskMaterials
Items included two clown dolls (one red, one blue); two visually distinct pots and a small ball for the unexpectedlocation false-belief prediction task; one prototypical candy tube (Smarties/M&Ms) con- taining a pencil for the deceptivecontentsfalse-beliefprediction task; three prototypical boxes (BandAid box, egg box, cereal box); three plain boxesandsix handpuppets(threeboy puppets,threegirl puppets) for thetwo unexpectedlocationfalse-beliefexplanationtasksandone true-belieffiller task;andone "lock-a-block" box (200-mmcube)with large plastic child-friendly key, one princesshandpuppet,one pirate handpuppet,and chocolategold coins for the sabotage/deceptiotnask.
Procedure Theory-of-Mind Tasks
At each time point, children were presentedwith eight false-belief tasks(five predictiontasks,threeexplanationtasks)andtwo deception tasks.Thesetasksare summarizedbriefly below.
False-beliepfredictiontasks. Thesetasksprovide a crucial test for children's understandingof the representationaland fallible nature of b e l i e f . A t e a c h t i m e p o i n t , c h i l d r e n w e r e p r e s e n t e dw i t h t w o u n e x p e c t e d location tasks, two unexpectedidentity tasks, and one emotion false- belief task. In the unexpectedlocation task (adaptedfrom Wimmer & Perner, 1983), the children were told a story involving a target object (e.g., a ball), two opaquecontainers(e.g., a box and a basket), and two puppetcharacters.In this story,onepuppetmovedthetargetobject while theotherpuppetwasabsent.Theuninformedpuppetthenreturned and expresseda desire for the target object. Children were asked to predict in which of the two containersthe puppet would look. Children were also asked a reality control question (e.g., "Where is the ball really?") andamemorycontrolquestion(e.g.,"Wheredidthepuppet leavethe ball?" ), and they were only codedas successfulif they gave correctresponsesto all of thecontrol questionsandto thetestquestion on eachtask.
In the unexpectedidentity tasks, children were either shown a box with deceptivecontents(e.g., a biscuit box that containeda toy animal) or told a story from a peep-throughpop-up book, in which the final page included an elementwith a deceptiveidentity (e.g., a spot on a snake'sback, which throughthe hole on the previouspagehad looked like aneye).Forthepeep-throughstorybooktasks,childrenwereasked what they could seeboth before and after turning the last page(belief- control and reality-control questions).Turning back to the penultimate page, children were introduced to a naive puppet and were asked to predict what the puppet would think the picture was before looking at the last page. For the deceptivecontentstask, both before and after openingthebox,childrenwereaskedwhattheythoughtwasinside.The box wasthenclosedover,andthechildrenwereagainaskedto predict what a naivepuppetwould think wasinsidethebox. Childrenwereonly c o d e d a s s u c c e s s f u li f t h e y g a v e c o r r e c t r e s p o n s e st o a l l o f t h e c o n t r o l questionsand to the test questionon each task.
At eachtimepoint,childrenalsoreceivedoneofthreeemotionfalse- beliefpredictiontasks,basedonthestorydevelopedby Harris,Johnson, Hutton, Andrews, and Cooke (1989). This task is designedto test chil- dren'sunderstandingof a character'sfalsebelief andalsohow thechar- acterwill feelasaresultofthatfalsebelief.Thethreestoriesusedin the presentstudy involved a nice surprise,a nasty surprise,or a scary surprise,andthesewerecounterbalancedacrosstime points.In thenasty surprisestory,acharacter(naughtyMicky themonkey)exchangedhis friend's favorite drink (Coke) for a disliked drink (milk) while his friend was away. In the nice surprisestory, a characterexchangeda dislikedfoodforalikedfood,againinthefriend'sabsence.Inthescary surprisestory,eachcharacterattemptedto scaretheotherby hiding behindatreeandpretendingtoroarlike alion (butwhileonecharacter hid himself very well, the other could be seenfrom his hiding place). Children were credited with successon each story if they correctly statedwhat the friend thoughthe was gettingto eat/drink (or who each friend thought was behind the tree for the scary story), and what he was really getting to eat/drink (or who was really behind the tree). Children were also given an extra point if they could also predict how thefriend would feel in eachstory (possiblescore= 0-2).
F a l s e - b e l i eef x p l a n a t i o nt a s k s . T h e s e t a s k s w e r e o n t h e p u p p e t t a s k developedby Bartsch and Wellman (1989) and involved prototypical boxes and unexpectedlocation stories. FOr each story, children were presentedwith a prototypical box (e.g., an egg box) and a matching plain box and were shownthat the prototypical box was empty, whereas theplainboxcontainedthetargetobject(e.g.,atoyegg).A filler story, in which the prototypical box containedthe target object and the plain box was empty, was also included to preventchildren guessingthat the plain box (rather than the prototypical box) would always be full. For eachstory, the children were introducedto a puppet "who hasnot seen theseboxes before," who expresseda desire for the target object and walked toward the prototypical box. Children were asked, "Why is (puppet)lookingthere?"If nobelief-basedanswerwasgiven,children were promptedwith the question,"What does(puppet) think?" Chil-

 drenwereratedassuccessfuol neachstoryif theymadeeitherasponta- neousor a promptedreferenceto a mistakenbelief in explainingthe storycharacter'saction(possiblescore= 0-3).
Deceptiontasks. In additionto theabovestoryvignettes,two decep-
t i o n t a s k s w e r e u s e d a t e a c h t i m e p o i n t . T h e f i r s t o f t h e s e w a s S o d i a n andFrith's (1992) one-boxpuppetdeceptiongame.This four-condition t a s k i n v o l v e s n o t o n l y c o o p e r a t i v ea n d c o m p e t i t i v et r i a l s b u t a l s o p h y s i - cal versusverbal conditions(all four conditionswere counterbalanced acrosschildren). In the physical condition, children are shown a box
t h a t c a n b e l o c k e d u s i n g a l a r g e p l a s t i c k e y a n d a r e i n t r o d u c e dt o a n i c e princesspuppetand a meanburglar puppet.A chocolategold coin is hiddenin thebox on eachtrial, andthechildrenareinstructedto help the princess(cooperativetrial) and to make it difficult for the burglar to find the gold coin (competitivetrial). In the verbal condition,the key is removed,and the princessand burglar puppetsare madeto appear from adistanceandsay,"I wonderif thebox is lockedor open?If the box is locked,I won't bothermakingthejourney,it's sucha long way." Again, the children were encouragedto help the princessbut to make it difficult for theburglar,andtheywereaskedwhattheywouldtell the puppet: "Are you going to say the box is locked or open?" (word orderwascounterbalancedacrosschildren).Childrenscored1pointfor passingboth trials in both the verbal and the physical condition, so possiblescoresrangedfrom 0 to 2 points.
T h e s e c o n dt a s k w a s a p e n n y - h i d i n gg a m e , f a m i l i a r t o m o s t p r e s c h o o l - ersandusedrecentlyin studiesof childrenwith autism(Baron-Cohen, 1992;Oswald& Ollendick,1989).Theexperimenterhidacoinbehind herbackand,bringingbothhandsforwardwith thecoinconcealedin onehand,askedthechildtoguesswhichhandheldthecoin.Thiswas r e p e a t e df o r t h r e e t r i a l s , a f t e r w h i c h t h e e x p e r i m e n t e ra n n o u n c e dt h a t i t was now the child's turn to hide the coin. On each of the three test trials with the child as hider, children scored 1 point if they fulfilled three criteria: (a) invisible displacementof the coin, (b) both hands presentedfor guessing,and (c) coin concealedthroughout. Possible scoreson this task thereforerangedfrom 0 to 3 points.
Theory-of-mind aggregate. From the five types of theory-of-mind task(standardfalse-beliefprediction,emotionfalse-belief,false-belief explanation, sabotage/deceptiona, nd penny hiding), an aggregate theory-of-mindscorewascomputedby scalingeachscoreto a 0-6 range(tobalancethecontributionfromeachtypeoftask).Themaxi- mum scorewas therefore30 points at eachtime point. To avoid loss of data, we rated children who failed control questionson any particular taskashavingfailedthattask.Cronbach'salphafor thetheory-of-mind aggregatewas .68 at Time 1, .75 at Time 2, and .59 at Time 3, indicating fair to good scalereliability.
Emotion Understanding Tasks
At Times 1 and 2, children'saffectivelabeling and affectiveperspec- tive-taking abilities were assessedusing the proceduresdevelopedby Denham(1986). (Children'sscoreson thesetasksapproachedceiling at Time 2, and so the taskswere not repeatedat Time 3.)
Affective labeling. Children were shown four felt facesportraying happy,sad,angry,andfrightenedexpressionsT. hey wereaskedto iden- tify the emotion portrayedin each face, first expressively,by naming, andthenreceptively,by pointingto theexpressionnamedby theexperi- menter.The code for scoring on this task was exactly the sameas that usedby Denham(1986). Childrenreceived2 pointsfor correctnaming or pointing; 1 point for identifying the correctvalencebut mistakingthe specificemotion(e.g.,callingthefrightenedfacesad);and0pointsfor givingawrongvalenceemotion(e.g.,callingthefrightenedfacehappy) or for failing to provide a response.The maximumpossiblescorefor affectivelabelingwastherefore16 points(expressiveandreceptiveiden- tification of four emotions).
Affectiveperspectivetaking. In thistask,puppets(with blankfaces) wereusedtoenact17vignettesportrayingsituationsinwhichtheprotag- onistfelthappiness,sadness,anger,orfear,suchasgoingtothezoo,
seeinga parentoff on a trip, havinga toy hiddenby a sibling, or having a bad dream,respectively.Each of the storieswas actedout with vocal and facial cuesfor the puppet'sfeelings.Eight of the vignetteswere unambiguous,inthatthepuppet'semotionwaswhatmostpeoplewould b e e x p e c t e dt o f e e l i n t h a t s i t u a t i o n . T h e o t h e r 9 v i g n e t t e sw e r e a m b i g u - ous, in that the puppet'semotiondiffered from the emotionpreviously p r e d i c t e d b y t h e m o t h e r f o r t h e c h i l d . A t t h e e n d o f e a c h s t o r y , t h e children were askedhow the protagonistfelt. Children could respond verbally or nonverballyby selectingthe appropriatefelt face to stick onto the puppet (children were creditedwith their best answersin the rare caseof giving contradictoryverbal and nonverbalresponses)R. e- sponseswerescoredasin theaffectivelabelingtask(maximumpossible totalscore= 34points).FollowingDenham(1986),anaggregatescore foraffectivelabelingandaffectiveperspectivetakingwascreatedby combining the children's scoreson the two sets of tasks (maximum possiblescore= 50). Cronbach'salphafor the aggregatescorewas .85 at Time 1 and .68 at Time 2, indicating good scalereliability.
Emotion interview. At Time 2, childrenwerealsointerviewedabout t h e r e a l - l i f e c a u s e s o f h a p p i n e s s s, a d n e s s a, n g e r , a n d f e a r f o r t h e m s e l v e s , their friends, and their mothers.This interview was basedon that used by Cassidy,Ross,Butkovsky,andBraungart(1992) andis reported morefully in J. Dunn andHughes(1998). In brief, childrenwereshown f o u r p i c t u r e c a r d s r e p r e s e n t i n ga h a p p y f a c e , a s a d f a c e , a n a n g r y f a c e , a n d a s c a r e d f a c e . A f t e r t h e c h i l d h a d c o r r e c t l y i d e n t i f i e d w h a t e m o t i o n e a c h f a c e r e p r e s e n t e d t, h e f i r s t f a c e w a s s h o w n a n d t h e c h i l d w a s a s k e d fourquestions:(a)Whatkindsofthingsmakeyoufeelthisway?(b) Canyougivemeanexampleofatimeyoufeltthisway.., thenwhat happened?(c) Let's pretendyou saw(friend'sname)looking this w a y - - w h y d o y o u t h i n k s h e / h e m i g h t b e l o o k i n g l i k e t h a t ? ( d ) L e t ' s pretendyou saw your Mum looking this way? Why do you think she might be looking like that? The procedurewas repeatedfor each of the four emotions. The children's responseswere tape-recordedand transcribedverbatim following the session.They were then coded in termsof theme,agent(referredto ascause),andadequacy.Theresults presentedin this article are from the adequacycoding. Responseswere codedona0-4-pointscale:0 = noresponse,refusal,don'tknow;1= poor response(including irrelevantremarks,failure to understandcausal natureof question,or causesuggestedthat is very unlikely to provoke emotioninquestion);2= adequateresponse(includingonewordor simple clauseonly, but appropriateand plausibleresponse;e.g., "mon- sters" as a reply to the questionof what made a friend scared); 3 = goodresponse(including relevantappropriatesentenceresponseor two or more adequateresponses)4; = excellent response(including elabo- rate responseor evidenceof insight; e.g., mentionof mixed emotions, transienceof emotion~tl experience).Examplesfor happinessin self follow: "Fireworks. They're going to be at the 1 o'clock club. I'll be very happy becauseI haven't seenit before." or "When your Mum brings you a presentas it's your birthday, and then you feel sad again becausethe birthday is finished." Agreementbetweenthe two coders wasassessedfor 25 children.Thevalueof Cohen'skappafor adequacy ratings was .87, indicating excellent interrater reliability. Cronbach's alphafor the overall adequacyscorewas .91, indicatingexcellentscale reliability.
Mixed-emotionstask. At Time 3, children'sunderstandingof mixed emotionswas assessedusing the proceduresdevelopedby Gordis et al. (1989). The first part of this task consistsof threeshortvignettes,each i n v o l v i n g a p r o t a g o n i s tw h o h a s m i x e d f e e l i n g s a b o u t a s i t u a t i o n ( e . g . , feelinghappyaboutwinningaraceagainstafriend,butalsofeelingsad becausethat friend fell down in the race). Children were askedto give a reasonfor eachemotionexpressedby the story character.In the next threevignettesin the secondpart of the task, the mixed emotionsof the story charactersare not made explicit. Here, children were asked to identifyhowtheprotagonist(X) feelsandtoexplainthatemotion.In thispartof thetask,childrenwereassistedby theprompt"DoesX feel anythingelse?Why doesshe/hefeel that way?" For both partsof the task,childrenwerecreditedwith0-2 pointsforeachvignette.Toreceive
UNDERSTANDING MIND AND MENTAL-STATE TALK 1029

 1030 HUGHES AND DUNN
2 points, children had to provide an adequateexplanation for why a charactermight simultaneouslyexperiencepositiveandnegativefeelings about a given situation. Children who providedadequateexplanations for only oneemotionor explainedsuccessivepositiveandnegativefeel- ings were creditedwith 1 point; all other answersscoredzero. In the thirdpartofthetask,childrenwereaskedtogiveanaccountofatime in which they had themselvesexperiencedmixed emotions.However, few childrenin the study wereable to do this, and so aggregatescores werecalculatedfrom the first two partsonly (maximumscore= 12). A Cronbachs' alphaof .53 wasobtainedfor this aggregatescore,indicat- ing fair scalereliability.
Coding Mental-StateTalk
In transcribing the videotapesof the children'sdyadic play sessions, wedefinedaconversationatlurnasall ofonechild'sutterancesbounded by the utterancesof the friend. The total numberof child utterancesat Times 1,2, and3 was4,748,6,740,and8,220,respectively(grandtotal = 19,746utterances)T.heanalysesfocusonconversationalturnsthat included a term denoting a mental state (n = 167,332, and 421, at Times1,2,and3,respectively)R.eliabilityoftranscriptionwaschecked by Claire Hughes,who transcribeda 5-rain sectionof eachvideo (i.e., 25% of all transcripts).Good agreementwas found for number of speakerturns, r(49) = .96, and number of mental-stateturns, r(49)
= .95.
Codingof mental-statetermswasbasedonearlierstudiesof children's
discourse(Shatz,Wellman,& Silber,1983;Furrow,Moore,Davidge,& Chiasson,1992;Brown et al., 1996). The termsincluded all referredto cognitive mental states (e.g., know, think, pretend, forget, remember, wonder,imagine, dream) and did not include referencesto desiresor feelings, becausethesestatesare not explicitly representational.The functional meaningof eachmental-statetermwascodedfollowing Shatz et al.'s system,using the modificationsdescribedin Brown et al. (1996) to include "conversational"as well as "genuine" usesof mental-state terms. The four categoriesderived from the transcripts are as follows:
1. Genuinementalreferenceincludedall turns in which the speaker referredto his or her own or another'sthoughts,beliefs,memories,and soon(e.g.,"Do youthink CaptainHookcouldbeapoliceman?")The phrase"I don't know" without a predicatecomplementwas also in- cludedin this category.Contrastives,in which children explicitly con- trasted a belief with reality or with anotherperson'sbelief, were also includedin this category; however,thesecontrastiveswere extremely rare (only one or two examplesat eachtime point).
2. Modulationof assertionincluded mental-state terms used to strengthenor weakenanassertion(e.g.,"It's Caspertheghost,I think" ) and acknowledgmentsof the other child's utterance (e.g., "Yes, I know").
3. Directinginteractionincludedturns in which the child introduced an activity with a mental-state term (e.g., "Let's pretend we're pirates").
4.Otherincludedclarifications(e.g.,"Doyoumeanthisone?), nouns,adverbs,and adjectives(e.g., "It's not a real shark, it's only a pretendone).
The referentof a mental-stateterm was codedinto threecategories: self, other (usually the child's friend), and child plus friend (e.g., "We think it's a dragon"). Theselast two categorieswere later collapsed together,to determinetotal frequencyof mentaltermsthat includedthe other.Thepragmaticcontextof theutterancewasalsocategorizedin threeways: (a) self-interes(te.g., "I think Mummieswearhigh heels, so I'll havethese");(b) neutral commentary(e.g., "I think the blue one is best"); and (c) sharedinterest (e.g., "We're pretendingwe're cooking, aren'twe?"). Reliability was checkedby double-coding20% ofthetranscriptsateachtimepoint.Excellentinterraterreliability values wereobtained(all Cohenkappavalues> .80).
Results
BackgroundMeasuresof Participants'Ability
At Time 1, the group mean standardindex of verbal ability on the British PictureVocabularyScalewas 120.92 (SD = 15.90). This index is normed around a mean of 100 (SD = 15). The high meanverbal ability for the group reflectsthe fact that children were recruited on the basis of their close friend- ships: It is likely that young children who develop such early friendshipsare verbally more able than their peers,a point that is worth recalling in consideringthe main resultsof this study. In contrast,the group mean standardindex of nonverbalability was54.2(SD= 10.5),closetothepopulationnorm50(SD= 10), suggestingage-appropriatenonverbalabilty for the group.
DevelopmentalChangeand Stability of Individual Differences
DevelopmentalChangein TaskPerformances
For understandingemotion, the group mean aggregateDen- ham (1986) scorewas 36.90 (SD = 8.44) at Time 1 and 43.29 (SD = 5.10) at Time 2. Children's performancesat Time 2 approachedceiling(max.score= 50), andsotheDenhamtask was not includedat Time 3. For understandingbelief, the num- bers of successfulchildren on each type of task (false-belief prediction/explanationand deception)at each time point are summarizedin Table 1, together with group mean aggregate scores.Significantincreasesovertime in thenumberof success- ful participantswere found for both false-beliefpredictionand deceptiontasksbut not false-beliefexplanationtasks(seeTable 1 for chi-squarevalues). However, half of the group were al- ready successfulat false-beliefexplanation at Time 1, sug- gestingan earlier time courseof improvementfor this kind of task.
Within-child developmentalchangesin aggregatescoresfor understandingemotion and belief were examinedin separate repeatedmeasuresanalysesof variance(ANOVAs) with age, verbal ability, and nonverbalability at Time 1 treatedas covari- ates.Children'saggregatescoresfor understandingemotionin- creasedsignificantlyovertime, F( 1, 98) = 51.7,p < .001, and both age and nonverbal ability showed significant covariance with Time 1 Denham scores(/3 = .36 and .38, respectively,p < .01 for both). Within-child improvementsin theory-of-mind scoreswerealsohighly significant,F(2, 147) = 19.4,p < .001, and again both age and nonverbal ability showed significant covariancewith theory of mind (/3 = .47 and .41, respectively,
p< .001forboth).Nogendereffectswerefoundforaggregate scoresof emotion or belief understanding,and there were no significant interaction terms. The lack of covariancebetween verbal ability and understandingbelief and emotion is puzzling but probably reflects the generally high verbal ability of this group.
DevelopmentalChangein Mental-StateTalk
Almost all of the children (49 out of 50) showeda steady logarithmic increasein their rate of mental-statetalk acrossthe three time points. The nature of mental-statereference(func- tional category,referent,andpragmaticcontext)is summarized

 aA ceiling effect was obtainedat Time 2, so this task was not given at Time 3. ** p < .01.
for the group at eachtime point in Table 2. To adjustfor skew- ness,we conductedrepeatedmeasuresANOVAs I on log-trans- formed data.The first ANOVA examinedwithin-child effectsof time (Times 1, 2, and 3) and functional category of mental-
state terms (genuine reference, modulation of assertion, and directing activity), as well as between-childeffects of gender. The main effects of time and function were both significant, F(2, 147) = 9.6 and 41.4, respectively,p < .001 for both, and therewas a significantTime x Functioninteraction,F(4, 145) = 17.6, p < .001, as well as a marginally significant Gender x Functioninteraction,F(3, 146) = 2.9,p = .06. Posthoc analy- ses showed that genuine mental-statereferencewas more fre- quentthanconversationaol r colloquial useof mental-stateterms at all time points; this difference increasedover time and was marginally more pronouncedfor girls than for boys.
A secondANOVA was conducted to examine within-child effects of time (Times 1, 2, 3) and referentfor the mental-state term (own vs. other/shared),as well as between-childeffects of gender.The results were similar to those above: Significant maineffectswerefoundfor bothtime,F(2, 147) = 13.7,p < .001, andreferent,F( 1, 98) = 6.7,p < .01, with a strongTime x Referentinteraction,F(3, 146) = 39.2,p < .001. Posthoc analysesshowedthat children referredto their own mental states significantly more often than to others' or sharedmental states at Times 1 and 2, but this difference disappearedat Time 3.
A third ANOVA was conductedto examine within-child ef- fects of time (Times 1, 2, 3) and pragmatic context of mental- state reference (self-interest, neutral commentary, and shared interest), as well as effects of gender. Again both time and context showed significant main effects, F(2, 147) = 9.1 and 35.3, respectively,p < .001 for both, and there was a strong Time x Context interaction,F(4, 145) = 26.8, p < .001. Post hoc analysesshowedthat at Time 1, most mental-statereference was made in the context of neutral commentary,but at Time 2, and especiallyTime 3, most mental-stateterms occurred in the context of sharedinterest.
Stability of Individual Differences
Table3 showsthefull correlations(at andbetweeneachtime point) for both aggregateand individual task scoresfor belief andemotionunderstanding,aswell asfor hourly ratesof mental- state talk. When aggregatetheory-of-mind scores were com- pared over time, individual differenceswere very stable, r(49)
1Theseanalyseswerealsorun with effectsof initial ageandability covariedout, with no changein resultsor significancelevels.
Table 2
Mean Frequenciesof Mental-State(MS) Talk at Each Time Point
Variable
Speakerturns/hr M
Time point
1 2 3
252.0 254.8 351.3
F(2, 147) 16.7"*
13.5"*
SD 78.8 MS terms/hr
M 10.0
SD 10.1 MS terms/turn
M 0.04
SD 0.04 GenuineMS reference/hr
M 3.5
SD 5.0 Modulatory MS reference/hr
M 1.9
SD 3.0 Directing MS reference/hr
M 3.2
SD 5.4 Referenceto own MS/hr
M 7.1
SD 8.3 Referenceto other/shared
MS/hr
M 3.0 SD 4.7
Self-interestedMS reference/hr
M 1.6 SD 3.4
NeutralMS reference/hr
M 5.9 SD 6.0
Shared-interesMt S reference/hr
131.2 114.3
18.4 22.1 21.5 19.9
M 2.4
SD 4.1 10.8 7.1
*p < .05. **p < .01.
UNDERSTANDING MIND AND MENTAL-STATE TALK
1031
Table 1
Numberof SuccessfuPl articipantsfor Each Theory-of-MindTaskandAggregateScoresat Each TimePoint
Task
Predict action from false belief Predictemotionfrom falsebelief Explain action from false belief Pennyhiding
Deception
Theory of mind aggregatescore M
SD
Criterion for success
Passboth tasks Passbothemotionandfalse-beliefquestion Pass2/3tasks
Passz~trials
Passall 4 conditions
Time point
1 2 3
18 23 33 10 19 31 26 32 31 25 34 43 28 43 a
14.3 18.7 21.4 7.3 8.1 6.6
X2(1, 50)
9.3** 18.5"* 1.7 14.9"* 16.4"*
F(2, 49)
19.4"*
8.8** 0.07 0.06
0.08 0.05
22.3**
12.8 14.3 17.9 15.3
5.9* 1.8 3.9
2.9 4.5
2.4 1.1 1.8 2.2
3.2*
28.4** 8.1 11.0
8.9 9.9
15.9"*
10.1 10.7 15.3 14.4
3.9 1.9 8.9 5.4
5.8 3.7 8.1 5.3
2.4 0.4
41.0"* 8.0 17.0

 1032 HUGHES AND DUNN Table 3
PearsonCorrelations BetweenTaskPerformanceand Mental-StateTalk at Each Time Point
Variable 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
1. T1 ToM total 2. T1 1st-orderFB 3. T1 emotionFB 4. T1 explain FB 5. T1 penny
6. T1 deception 7. T1 Denham
8. T1 MS/hr
9. T2 ToM total
10. T2 lst-orderFB 11. T2 emotionFB 12. T2 explain FB 13. T2 penny
14. T2 deception 15. T2 Denham 16. T2 Cassidy 17. T2 ms/hr
18. T3 ToM total 19. T3 lst-orderFB 20. T3 emotionFB 21. T3 explainFB 22. T3 penny
23. T3 Gordis
24. T3 ms/hr
.70** --
.69**
.50**
.45**
.47**
.39**
.21
.51"*
.28*
.40**
.45**
.19
.16
.47**
.23
.41"*
.34*
.12
.48**
.00
.00
.42**
.18 .30* .06
.47** - - .44** .30* .11 .16 .15 .16 .41"* .16 .26 -.02 .45** .25 .28* .09 .46** .30* .42** .24 .08 .13 .47** .00 .55** .29 .26 ..09 .45** .30* .20 .11 .01 .09 .38** .26 .11 .07
- -
-.13 -- -.02 .30*
.60** -.09 .29* .22 .54** .13 .46** .06 .46** .06 .45** .08 .32* -.03 .09 -.01 .45** .00 .46 -.10 .53** -.09 .38** .09 .36** -.07 .47** .24 .15 -.25 .09 -.01 .64** -.04 .29** .07
--
-.03 --
-.09 -.02 .52** .27
Note. N = 50. T1 = Time 1; ToM = theory of mind; FB = false belief; Denham= Denham's(1986) study; MS/hr = numberof mental-state *p <.05. **p <.01.
= .51, .58, .34 for Times 1-2; Times 2-3; and Times 1-3, respectively,p < .05 for all. Correlationsbetweenadjacenttime p o i n t s r e m a i n e d s i g n i f i c a n t e v e n w h e n i n d i v i d u a l d i f f e r e n c e s i n verbalandnonverbalability atTime 1werepartialedout, r(49) = .38and.46forTimes1-2 andTimes2-3,p < .01forboth. Correlationsbetweeneachtypeof theory-of-mindtaskarealso shownin Table3, becausetherelationshipbetweenperformance on different types of theory-of-mindtask is of topical interest (e.g., Holmes, Black, & Miller, 1996). Early individual differ- encesin bothpredictingandexplainingfalsebeliefwerecorre- lated with each other and were relatively stable over the 13- monthperiod (although,asexpected,many of thesecorrelations fell below significance once effects of verbal and nonverbal ability were taken into account). However, the deceptiontasks were not correlated with the other theory-of-mind tasks, and this could not be attributedto a floor effect (seeTable 1). One possibleaccountfor this dissociationis that deceptionplaces much strongerdemandsthan understandingfalse belief upon executive functions such as inhibitory control2 (see Hughes, 1998).
Performanceon the Denham (1986) task was also stable betweenTime 1 and Time 2, even when effects of both verbal and nonverbal ability were removed, r(49) = .60, p < .001. There was also good agreementbetweenthe different measures of emotionunderstandingusedat eachtime point. In particular, with effects of verbal and nonverbalability removed,children's scoreson the mixed-emotiontask were highly correlatedwith both the adequacyof their interview response6 months earlier, r(49) = .64,p < .001,andwith scoresfor affectiveperspective taking 13 months earlier, r(49) = .50, p < .001. Individual
differencesin children'semotionunderstandingwere therefore robust acrossmeasuresand stableover a 13-monthtime period.
D e s p i t e t h e l o g a r i t h m i c i n c r e a s ei n t h e f r e q u e n c y o f c h i l d r e n ' s useof mentalstateterms,individual differencesin mental-state talkwerealsostable.Correlationsacrossadjacenttimepoints remainedsignificantevenwheneffectsof verbalandnonverbal ability at Time 1 were removed,r(49) = .31 and .30 for Time 1-2 andTime 2-3, p < .05. That is, within the specificcontext of dyadic play between friends, individual differences in fre- quencyof mental-statetalk appearedreliableacrossa 13-month period.
RelationsBetweenDomains
Are Individual Differencesin UnderstandingMind and Emotion Associated?
The correlations for all three time points between perfor- manceson tests of theory of mind and emotion understanding (as well as rates of mental-statetalk) are shown in Table 3. As the table indicates, children's performanceswere closely correlatedboth within and acrosstasks of understandingbelief
z T h i s p r o p o s a l d i f f e r s f r o m R u s s e l l , M a u t h n e r , S h a r p e ,a n d T i d s w e l l ' s (1991) account, in that inhibitory control is predicted to be more strongly related with deceptionthan with false-beliefunderstanding, b e c a u s eo n l y d e c e p t i o n e n t a i l s c o m m u n i c a t i o nt h a t r u n s d i r e c t l y c o u n t e r to theGriceantruthmaxim(seeHughes,1998).
-.10
.07 .64**
-.01 .64** .02 .46** -.04 .49**
-.14 .37* .29* .27 -.02 .71"* -.12 .40**
.09 .55**
.22 .54** -.11 .46** .26 .46**
.09 .33*
.04 .29* -.09 .62** -.21 .18
.33*
--
.30* -- .33* .79** .19 .71"* .28* .81"* .09 .63** .25 .41"* .36** .51"* .16 .52** .44** .52** .45** .58** .31" .33* .37** .52** .28* .37** .24 .28* .39** .74** .29** .24

 .53** - - .33* .20 .43** .38** .47** .36** .40** .28** .41"* .36** .36** .27
- -
.32* --
.21 .46** -- .27 .47** .28**
- -
UNDERSTANDINGMIND AND MENTAL-STATE TALK 1033
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24
.58"*
.54** .45**
.35** .23
.27 .21
.37** .43**
.36** .51"*
.46** .40**
.49** .36**
.31" .32*
.46** .40** .39** .37** .24 .27 .26 .13 .20 .64** .66** .63** .27 .28** .24
--
.26 .18 .37** .44**
.28* .48** -.13 .25
.38** .30*
.22 .32 .50**
.31" .49** .81"* .29* .29* .30* .61"* .12 .17 .24 .60** .28* .64** .62** .47** .32* .10 .32* .18 .11
.24 .39** .33* .20 .10 .24 .37** .65** .35** .14
- -
-. 12
termsperhour;T2 = Time2;Cassidy= Cassidyetal.'s(1992)study;T3 = Time3;Gordis= Gordisetal.'s(1989)study.
and emotion (although associationswith performanceon the deceptiontasks were less consistent).In general,thesecorrela- tions remainedsignificant evenwhen individual differencesin general ability were taken into account: All but 10 individual task correlations significant at the p < .01 level in Table 3 remained significant (p < .05) when effects related to verbal and nonverbal ability were removed. (Although most correla- tions were significant at all three time points, the relations be- tweentasksappearedstrongestatTime2.Thismayreflectfloor and ceiling effects on sometasks at Time 1 and Time 3.)
The interdependencebetweenunderstandingbelief and emo- tion is well illustratedby theemotionfalse-belieftask,in which children were asked to predict both a story-character'sfalse belief and the emotion provoked by this belief. Becausethis task was originally developedas a test of understandingbelief, i t w a s i n c l u d e d w i t h i n t h e t h e o r y - o f - m i n d a g g r e g a t e .H o w e v e r , it could be arguedthat the task also measureschildren's under- standing of emotion. This dilemma was addressedempirically by using Fisher'sz transformsto comparethe strengthof corre- lations betweenemotion false-beliefperformanceand each ag- gregatescore(first subtractingemotionfalse-beliefscoresfrom the theory-of-mind aggregate).This analysis showed that at Time 1, emotion false-belief task was significantly more stronglycorrelatedwith theremainingtheorY-of-mindtasksthan withtheemotion-understandingaggregate,r(49) = .44and.16, z = 2.13, p < .05. At Times 2 and 3, this difference was nonsignificant,r(49) = .46 and .43; .56 and .49 at Times 2 and 3, respectively.Overall, then, performanceon this task was at least as closely associatedwith understandingbelief as with understandingemotion.
Close ties between understandingfalse belief and emotion were also apparentwhen the relation betweenaggregatescores in eachdomain was examinedacrosstime points. For example, a regressionanalysis showedthat initial differencesin emotion understanding predicted aggregate theory-of-mind scores 13 months later (/3 = .54, R2 = .29), F(I, 48) = 20.0, p < .001. (Note that the standardizedregressioncoefficient beta hutomaticallycontrolsfor differencesin rangebetweenmea- sures.)A stepwiseregressionanalysiswas carried out to exam- inewhetherthepredictiverelationbetweenearlyemotionunder- standingand later theory-of-mindperformancewas independent of age and ability. Age, verbal ability, nonverbal ability, and Time 1 theory-of-mind scoreswere enteredat the first step of the regression,so that autocorrelationwithin theory-of-mind performance was controlled. Together these factors predicted 3 2 % o f t h e v a r i a n c e i n T i m e 3 t h e o r y - o f - m i n d s c o r e s ( R 2 = .32), F(4, 45) = 7.1, p < .001. At the secondstep, Time 1 emotion-understandingscores independentlypredicted Time 3 theory-of-mind scores(/3 = .32, p < .05; AR 2 = .06), F(5, 44) = 5.4,p < .05.
Separateregressionanalyseswere conductedto examinethe predictorsof mixed-emotionunderstandingat Time 3. In a sim- ple linear regression,initial theory-of-mindperformancewas a significant predictor of performanceon the mixed emotion task (Gordisetal., 1989) 13-monthslater(/3 = .42;R2= .18), F(1, 48) = 10.2, p < .01. As before, a stepwiseregressionanalysis was then carried out to examine whether this associationwas independentof age and ability, controlling for autocorrelations within emotion understanding.Age, verbal ability, nonverbal ability, and affective perspectivetaking were all enteredat the
.35** - - .38** .16 .49** .30* .28* .26
- -
.24 .04
- -
.32*

 1034 HUGHES
AND DUNN
first step and togetherpredicted48% of the variancein Time 3 Gordis scores,F(4, 45) = 12.2,p < .001, althoughonly age (/3 = .30) and affective perspective-taking(/3 = .37) scores were significantlypredictiveof scoresfor understandingmixed emotionat Time 3. Adding Time 1 theory-of-mindscoresat the secondstep did not increasethe explainedvariancein Time 3 Gordis scores,indicatingno independenteffect of early differ- encesin understandingbelief in predicting later differencesin understandingmixed emotions.
RelationsBetweenTaskPerformances and Mental-StateTalk
Even when effects of verbal and nonverbalability were par- tialed out, individual differencesin children's hourly rates of mental-statetalk at Time 1 were significantly correlated(p < .05) with performance13 monthslater in false-beliefexplana- tion, r(49) = .31; in predictingactionsor emotionsbasedon false belief, r(49) = .31 and .29, respectively;and in under- standingmixedemotions,r(49) = .50.Theseassociationswere investigatedusing stepwiseregressionanalyses,to control for effects of age, generalability, and autocorrelationeffects.
The first analysisexaminedwhether initial rates of mental- statetalk predictedaggregatetheory-of-mindscoresat Time 3. Whenconsideredaloneasapredictorof theory-of-mindperfor- m a n c e , i n i t i a l r a t e s o f m e n t a l - s t a t et a l k a c c o u n t e df o r 2 0 % o f the variancein Time 3 theory-of-mindscores(/3 = .45, Re = .20), F(1, 48) = 12.0, p < .001. Note that this relation was not strengthenedwhen only "genuine" mental-statereferences were included(/3 = .36, R2 = .13), F(I, 48) = 7.0, p < .01. Next, a stepwiseregressionanalysiswas conductedto examine whetherthe longitudinalassociationbetweenindividual differ- encesin initial rates of mental-statetalk and Time 3 theory-of- mind performancewas independentof effects related to age, generalability, and autocorrelationwith initial theory-of-mind performance.Age, verbal ability, nonverbalability, and Time 1 theory-of-mindscoreswereenteredat thefirst stepof theregres- sion, and together explained 32% of the variance in Time 3 theory-of-mindscores(R2= .32),F(3,46)=7.1,p<.001.At the secondstep,Time 1 frequencyof mental-statetalk remained marginallysignificantlyassociatedwith Time 3 theory-of-mind s c o r e s ( / 3 = . 2 5 , A R 2 = . 0 5 ) , F ( 5 , 4 4 ) = 5 . 2 , p = . 0 7 . N o t e t h a t the reverserelation,betweeninitial theory-of-mindperformance andTime3mental-statetalk,wasnonsignificant(/3= .18), even before factors such as age and ability were taken into account.
The secondanalysisexaminedwhetherinitial ratesof mental- state talk predicted mixed-emotionunderstandingat Time 3. When mental-statetalk was consideredalone as a predictor of Time 3 mixed-emotionscores, a significant associationwas found(/3= .39,R2= .15),F(1,48) = 8.8,p < .005.However, astepwiseregressionanalysiswith age,verbalability,nonverbal ability, andTime 1Denhamscores(Denham,1986)enteredat the first stepshowedthat thesevariablestogetherexplained48% ofthevarianceinTime3theory-of-mindscores(R2= .48), F ( 4 , 4 5 ) = 1 2 . 2 , p < . 0 0 1 ; a n d T i m e 1 m e n t a l - s t a t et a l k e n t e r e d a t t h e s e c o n d s t e p d i d n o t i n c r e a s et h e e x p l a i n e d v a r i a n c e , i n d i - cating that the associationbetweeninitial mental-statetalk and Time 3 emotion understandingwas not independentof effects relatedto thesefactors. Note also from Table 3 that the correla-
tion betweenTime 1 Denhamperformanceand Time 3 mental- state talk was nonsignificant,and so this relationshipwas not examined.
GenderDifferences
No effects of genderwere found for any task measureat any time point (see DevelopmentaCl hangein TaskPerformances, in the Resultssection). However, a repeated-measureAsNOVA of (log transformed)mental-statetalk (with standardvocabu- lary scores at Time 1 covaried) showed that girls displayed more frequent referenceto mental states than boys, both per hour,F(1,48)=4.6,p< .05,andperspeakerturn,F(1,48) = 6.6, p < .01. Although the Gender× Time interactionterms were nonsignificant,differences between boys and girls was clearestat the final time point. Posthoc analyses(Tukey'shon- estly significantdifference)at this time point showedthat girls displayedmore mental-statetalk than boys per hour, F( I, 48) = 7.9,p < .01, andper speakerturn, F(I, 48) = 12.2,p < .001. Girls also used a greater variety of mental-stateterms, F(1, 48) = 5.8, p < .02; madea greaternumberof genuine mental-statereferencesper hour, F(1, 48) = 5.6, p < .02; and showeda greaternumberof mental-statereferencesin the pragmaticcontext of sharedinterest,F(1, 49) = 5.8, p < .02. However,thesefindingsshouldnotbetreatedasseparateeffects, b e c a u s et h e o b s e r v a t i o n a lm e a s u r e sa r e h i g h l y i n t e r c o r r e l a t e d , r(49) < .75,p < .001.Instead,thesefindingsprovideconverg- ing evidencethat mental-statetalk is both more frequent and developmentallymore advancedin girls comparedwith boys.
Discussion
Themainfindingsof thestudycanbesummarizedasfollows. As expected,over the 13 monthsof the study, children showed marked improvementsin their performanceon tests of under- standingfalsebeliefandaffectiveperspectivetaking.Individual differencesin thesetwo domainswere relatedto eachother and stable over time. In addition, performanceon both theory-of- mind andemotionunderstandingtaskswascorrelatedwith the frequencyof children'smental-statetalk in dyadic play with friends. In fact, initial individual differencesin the frequencyof m e n t a l - s t a t et a l k i n t h i s s o c i a l c o n t e x t w e r e s i g n i f i c a n t l y a s s o c i - ated with theory-of-mindperformancemore than a year later. Significantdevelopmentaclhangewasalsoobservedinthecon- versations recorded between friends. For example, children showed a steady logarithmic increasein their hourly rates of mental-statetalk over the course of the study. Children also showedthreeimportantqualitativechangesin their mental-state talk acrosstime: (a) an increasein the proportion of genuine referencesto mentalstates;(b) a shift from referringprimarily totheirownmentalstatestoreferringatleastasoftentoshared or others'mentalstates;and(c) arelatedshift awayfrom men- tal-statetalk asneutralcommentarytowardmental-statetalk in the context of sharedinterest.
Whataretheimplicationsoftheabovefindingsfortheissues r a i s e d i n t h e i n t r o d u c t i o n ? I n t h e i r e a r l y l o n g i t u d i n a l i n v e s t i g a - t i o n o f t h e r e l a t i o n s a m o n g t h e o r y o f m i n d , e m o t i o n u n d e r s t a n d - ing, and young children's interactions with others, J. Dunn, Brown, Slomkowski,et al. ( 1991) highlightedboth the continu- ity in individual differencesbetweenchildren and the potential

 positiveeffectsof child-child interactions(in the caseof sib- lings) on children'sgrowing mental awareness.The resultsof this study supporteachof theseconclusions.Individual differ- encesbetweenchildren were stableover 13 months, both for taskperformancesandfor observationaml easuresof children's conversationalreferenceto mental states.The stability in task performanceprovidesa reassuringcounterpointto recentsug- gestionsthat false-belieftaskshave poor test-retestreliability (Mayes et al., 1996) and confirms the utility of the multitask aggregateapproachusedin thepresentstudy.
The stability of mental-statetalk is also important, as it pro- videsa first steptowardexploringthe significanceof individual differencesin young children's referenceto mental statesin their conversationswith friends. Previousstudies(e.g., Brown et al., 1996)haveindicatedsignificantdevelopmentalshiftsin key conversationapl artnersfor mental-statetalk. In this study, individual differencesin frequency of children's mental-state talk with friends were highly stable,indicating developmental continuity in children's mental-statereferencewithin specific conversationalcontexts.At the sametime, as outlined above, the resultsof this study also indicatedevelopmentacl hangesin the quality of children's mental-statetalk. However, these changes(e.g., increasein proportion of referenceto others' mentalstates)may simplyreflectbaselinechangesin children's interactionswith friends over time. This possibility deserves further study.
The presentresultsalsoextendfindingsfrom previousstudies focusedon siblingsthat indicatea positiveeffect of child-child interactionson children'sdevelopingsocialunderstanding(e.g., J. Dunn, Brown, Slomkowski,et al., 1991; Lewis et al., 1996; Perner et al., 1994). In this study, children who engagedin frequent referenceto mental statesin conversationswith their friendsnot only showedhigherconcurrentfalse-beliefunder- standingbut also were more likely than their peersto perform well on false-belieftasksmorethana yearlater.Remarkably, this relation remainedmarginally significant even when initial differencesin theory-of-mindperformance,age, verbal ability, andnonverbalability wereall takeninto account.
Another topic raised in the introduction was the ecological validity of laboratory-basedassessmentsof children's under- standingofmind.Theresultsofthisstudyofferqualifiedsupport for thesetasks.Children'sperformanceon standardfalse-belief tasks was correlatedwith their mental-statetalk at all three t i m e p o i n t s . H o w e v e r , o n c e i n d i v i d u a l d i f f e r e n c e s i n v e r b a l a n d nonverbalability were takeninto account,this relationfell be- low significanceattwo of thethreetimepoints.Moreover,al- though girls showedboth more frequent and developmentally moreadvancedmental-statetalk thanboys,therewereno gender differencesin performanceon thefalse-belieftasks.This sug- geststhat althoughlaboratorytasksprovidea quick methodof a s s e s s i n gc h i l d r e n ' s s o c i a l i n s i g h t , t h e y a r e l e s s l i k e l y t o p r o v e especiallysensitiveto individual differencesin how children applytheirunderstandingofmindtotheeverydaysocialworld.
Also raisedin the introduction was the questionof whether individual differencesin children'sunderstandingof emotions andbeliefsarerelated.UnlikethefindingsreportedbyJ.Dunn (1995), false-beliefperformanceand emotion understanding were closely associatedin this study. In fact, early affective perspectivetaking predictedtheory-of-mindperformance13 monthslater,evenwheninitial differencesin theoryof mind,
age,andgeneralability wereall takeninto account.Theseresults suggestcloselinks betweenchildren's understandingof feelings a n d t h e i r u n d e r s t a n d i n go f b e l i e f . T h e d i s c r e p a n c yb e t w e e n t h e presentfindings and thosereportedby J. Dunn (1995) can be explainedin at leasttwo ways. One possibleaccountis that the greaternumberof theory-of-mindtasksusedin thepresentstudy provideda morerobustaggregatethanthe singletaskmeasure usedbyJ.Dunn(1995).A secondpossibilityisthatthedifferen- tial sequelaeof understandingmind and emotionemergegradu- ally over development;whereasJ. Dunn (1995) comparedtask performanceat 40 months with social adjustment30 months later, the presentstudy involved only a 13-monthperiod. Some of the findings in the presentstudy are consistentwith this developmentalaccount.For example,althoughboth emotional perspectivetaking and false-beliefcomprehensionwere corre- latedwith mental-statetalk, oncefactorssuchasage,ability, and initial task performancewere taken into account,longitudinal associationswere more clear-cutbetweenmental-statetalk and later theory-of-mindperformanceratherthan later emotionun- derstanding.On balance, however, the results of the present study suggestgeneralratherthan specificrelationsbetweenso- cial understandingand conversationaldisplaysof mental-state awareness.
In contrastwith thepositedbroadnatureof relationsbetween mental-statetalk andsociocognitiveability, findingsfrom previ- ous studiessuggestspecificcontrastsin mental-statetalk across different conversationacl ontexts(e.g., with different conversa- tional partners,Brown et al., 1996; in pretendvs. nonpretend play, Hughes& Dunn, 1997). In addition,it hasbeenproposed that such context effects show developmentalchange(Brown et al., 1996). In support of this view, in the present study, conversationswere recordedbetweenfriends in the sameplay situationatallthreetimepoints,andyetthenatureofchildren's mental-statetalk changedsignificantlyover time. For example, therewasa strikingincreasein theproportionof mental-state referencesthat occurredwithin the context of sharedinterest. The simplest interpretation of this finding is that children showeda baselineincreasein their levelsof sharedinterestat each time point. This possibility is currently being addressed through a study of developmentalchangesin the coordination of playbetweentheseyoungfriends.
At the same time, context effects caution against drawing generalconclusionsabout developmentacl hangesin children's m e n t a l - s t a t et a l k f r o m a n y o n e s o c i a l s i t u a t i o n : C o n v e r s a t i o n s betweenolder friends or betweenchildren who are not close friends,orbetweenchildrenandtheirparents,maytelladiffer- ent developmentalstory. In the final part of this article, we comparethe presentmethodsand findings with thosereported by BartschandWellman(1995) in theirclassicstudyof chil- dren'stalk aboutthe mind.
F i r s t , t h e p r e s e n t s t u d y w a s b a s e d o n a s m a l l e r l a n g u a g e sample than the Child Language Data Exchange System (CHILDES; MacWhinney& Snow,1985)databaseusedby Bartschand Wellman's(1995) study (just under 20,000 utter- ancesas comparedwith 200,000). Second,the presentstudy involvedchildrenfrom a muchnarroweragerangethanwas possiblewith the CHILDES database(47-60 months,ascom- pared with 18-72 months in Bartsch and Wellman's study). Despitetheselimitations,thepresentstudyalsocarriedanum- berofadvantagesovertheCHILDESdatabaseF.irst,thecombi-
UNDERSTANDINGMIND
AND MENTAL-STATETALK 1035

 1036 HUGHESAND DUNN
nationofobservationaalndexperimentaalpproachesadoptedin
t h e p r e s e n t s t u d y e n a b l e d d i r e c t e m p i r i c a l c o m p a r i s o n st o b e madebetweendevelopmentaclhangesinchildren'smental-state t a l k a n d t h e i r i m p r o v i n g p e r f o r m a n c eo n t h e o r y - o f - m i n dt a s k s . Second,transcriptionfrom videotape(as comparedwith audio- tape)allowedmoresensitivecodingof thecontextof children's conversationsT. hird, 50 children were involved in this study (as opposedto only 10 in the CHILDES sample),improving the generalizabilityof the presentfindings and enablingissues of individualdifferencesto be addressed.
BartschandWellman( 1995) focusedon the onsetof specific mental-stateterms(ratherthantheirfrequency),andsoadopted t h e c o n s e r v a t i v es t r a t e g y o f r e s t r i c t i n g a n a l y s i s t o c a s e s o f " g e n - uine" mental-statereference(but includedtermsof desireas well ascognition).Previousresearchershavefoundthatmental- state terms typically appearin children'svocabulariesin the 3rd year of life (Bretherton,McNew, & Beeghly-Smith,1981). At the start of this study, the preschoolerswere all in their 4th year (precludingcalculationof onsetages),but becausethe datasetwas more tractablein size than the CHILDES dataset, i t w a s p o s s i b l e t o c a l c u l a t e f r e q u e n c i e so f m e n t a l - s t a t er e f e r e n c e . In addition,it hasbeenarguedthat children'sunderstandingof conversationaulsesof mental-statetermsto modulateassertions emergesin parallel with (and may dependon) developments in theory of mind (Moore, Bryant, & Furrow, 1989), and so conversationaul sesof mental-statetalk were includedin the presentstudy. In supportof the claim madeby Moore and his colleagues,"conversational"and "genuine" usesof mental- statetalk wereboth associatedwith theory-of-mindtaskperfor- mancein the presentstudy.
studyshoweda cleardevelopment!ashift, with a significant i n c r e a s eo v e r t i m e i n t h e p r o p o r t i o n o f m e n t a l - s t a t et e r m s u s e d to referto others'(ratherthantheirown) mentalstates.This s h i f t i s h a r d t o e x p l a i n w i t h i n t h e o r y - t h e o r y b u t i s c o n s i s t e n t with simulationtheory and with findings from anotherrecent studyof developmenitn youngchildren'smental-statetalk (Im- bens-Bailey,Prost, & Fabricius, 1997). However, before con- cludingthatthefindingsfrom thetwo studiesarecontradictory in this respect,one should recall that all the conversationsin thepresentstudywererecordedin thecontextof dyadicplay betweenfriends, whereasmost of the utterancesanalyzedby BartschandWellmanwerebetweenchildrenandadults.Conver- sationalpartnersare known to exert significantinfluenceson children'smental-statetalk (Brown et al., 1996; Furrow et al., 1992; Hughes& Dunn, 1997) andmay well explainthe discrep- ancy betweenfindings from the two studies.Alternatively, as Pemer(1996)suggestedi,tispossiblethatamixofboththeory- buildingandsimulationprocessesareinvolvedin children's developingunderstandingof mind. The situation we studied, play betweenfriends, through its demandsfor imaginaryand c o o p e r a t i v e i n t e r a c t i o n , m a y e s p e c i a l l y f o s t e r a n d s u p p o r t c h i l - dren'ssimulationsof others'minds.
References
Astington,J.W.,& JenkinsJ,.M. (1995).Theoryof minddevelopment andsocialunderstandin[gSpecialissue]. Cognition and Emotion, 9, 151-165.
Baron-CohenS, . (1992). Out of sightor out of mind?Anotherlookat deceptionin autism.Journal of Child PsychologyandPsychiatry,33, 1141-1155.
As can be seenfrom someof the methodologicadl ifferences
describedabove,the aims of the two studiesshouldbe seenas
complementaryH.owever,onatleastoneissue,thestudiesover-
lap and lead to different conclusionsT. his issueis the question
of developmentacl hangesin the referentof children'smental-
statetalk,aquestionthatispivotaltoanongoingdebatebetween
two contrastingperspectiveson children'smentalisticdevelop-
ment:theory-theoryandsimulationtheory.Thecentralclaimof
the theory-theoryview is that childrenacquirean understanding
of mind througha processof theorybuilding(suchthat a valid
analogycan be madebetweendevelopmentacl hangesin chil-
dren'sunderstandinogf mindandconceptuasl hiftswithin scien-
tific theories).This claim is basedon the assumptionthat chil-
drendo not haveprivilegedself-knowledgeof their own mental
statesbut ratherconstructa theory of mentallife that applies
equallyto selfandother(Gopnik, 1993).In contrast,simulation
theoryholdsthatchildrenbeginby identifyingtheirownmental
statesthroughintrospection,andthengeneralizethesemental
statesto otherpeoplethroughthe imaginativeprocessof "simu-
lation"--puttingoneselfin theplaceof anothersoasto vicari-
ouslyexperiencewhatthatpersonmightthinkorfeel(Gordon, tioninpreschoolersC:ontextuavlalidation.ChildDevelopment,57,
1986; Harris, 1991).
According to Bartsch and Wellman (1995), analysesof the
CHILDES databasesuggestno clear difference betweenthe
onsetfor children referring to their own versusothers' mental
states,andso supportthe theory-theoryaccountof development
in children'sunderstandingof mind (ratherthansimulationthe-
ory). The presentdatasetconcernsfrequencyof mental-state
talk(ratherthanageofonset),andsohaveonlytangential statesandchildren'slaterunderstandinogfothers'emotionsD.evelop- implicationsfor this debate.Nevertheless,the children in this mental Psychology,27, 448-455.
Bartsch,K., & Wellman,H. M. (1989). Youngchildren'sattributionof actionto belief anddesires.Child Development,60, 946-964.
Bartsch,K., & Wellman,H. M. (1995). Children talk about the mind. New York: OxfordUniversityPress.
Bretherton,I., McNew,S.,& Beeghly-SmithM, . (1981).Earlyperson knowledgeasexpressedingesturaalndverbalcommunicationW:hen do infantsacquirea "theory of mind"? In M. Lamb& L. Sherrod (Eds.), Social cognition in infancy (pp. 333-373). Hillsdale,NJ: Erlbaum.
Brody,L. R. (1985). Genderdifferencesin emotionaldevelopmenAt: reviewof theoriesandresearchJ.ournal of Personality,53, 102-149.
Brown,J. R., Donelan-McCallN, ., & Dunn,J. (1996). Why talk about mental states?The significanceof children's conversationswith friends,siblingsandmothers.Child Development,67, 836-849.
Brown,J. R., & Dunn,J. (1996). Continuitiesin emotionunderstanding from threeto six years.Child Development,67, 789-802.
Cassidy,J. C., Ross,D. P., Butkovsky,L., & BraungartJ, . M. (1992). Family-peerconnections:Therolesof emotionalexpressiveness within the familyandchildren'sunderstandinogf emotions.Child Development,63, 603-618.
Denham,S.A. (1986). Socialcognition,prosocialbehaviora, ndemo-
194-201.
Denham,S.A., McKinley,M., ConchoudE, .A., & Holt, R. (1990).
Emotionalandbehavioraplredictorsofpreschoopleerratings.Child
Development,61, 1145-1152.
Dunn,J. (1995). ChildrenaspsychologistsT:helatercorrelatesof indi-
vidualdifferencesin understandinogf emotionsandotherminds.Cog-
nition and Emotion, 9, 187-201.
Dunn,J., Brown,J. R., & BeardsallL, . ( 1991). Familytalk aboutfeeling

 Dunn, J., Brown, J. R., Slomkowski, C., Tesla, C., & Youngblade, L. ( 1991). Youngchildren'sunderstandingof otherpeople'sfeelingsand beliefs:IndividualdifferencesandtheirantecedentsC.hildDevelop- ment, 62, 1352-1366.
Dunn, J., & Hughes,C. (1998). Youngchildren'sunderstandingof emo- tions within close relationshipsCognition and Emotion 12, 2, 171-
190.
Dunn, L. M., Dunn, L. M., Whetton,C., & Pintilie, D. (1982). British
Picture VocabularyScale.Windsor,UK: NFER-Nelson.
Furrow, D., Moore, C., Davidge, J., & Chiasson,L. (1992). Mental termsin mothers'andchildren'sspeech:Similaritiesandrelationships.
Journal of Child Language, 19, 617-631.
Gopnik, A. (1993). How we know our minds: The illusions of first-
personknowledgeof intentionality.BehaviourandBrain Sciences,
16, 1-14.
Gordis,EW.,Rosen,A.B.,Grand,S.(1989,April). Youngchildren's
understandingof simultaneousconflicting emotions.Posterpresented a t t h e b i e n n i a l m e e t i n g o f t h e S o c i e t y f o r R e s e a r c hi n C h i l d D e v e l o p - ment,KansasCity, MO.
Gordon, R. M. (1986). Folk psychologyas simulation.Mind and Lan- guage, 1, 158-171.
Gottman,J.M. (1986).Theworldofcoordinatedplay:Same-andcross- sexfriendshipin youngchildren.In J.M. Gottman,& J.G. Parker (Eds.), Conversationsoffriends: Speculationson affective develop- ment(pp. 139-191). Cambridge,UK: CambridgeUniversityPress.
Happ6,E G.E.(1995).Theroleof ageandverbalabilityinthetheory- of-mind task performanceof subjectswith autism. Child Develop- ment, 66, 843-855.
Harris, P. L. ( 1991). The work of the imagination.In A. Whiten (Ed.), Natural theories of mind (pp. 283-304). Oxford, UK: Basil Blackwell.
Harris, E L., Johnson,C., Hutton, D., Andrews,G., & Cooke,T. (1989). Youngchildren'stheoryof mindandemotion.Cognition andEmotion, 3, 379-400.
Hartup, W. W. (1996). The companythey keep: Friendshipsand their developmentasl ignificance.Child Development,67, 1-13.
Holmes,H. A., Black, C., & Miller, S. A. (1996). A cross-taskcompari- son of false-beliefunderstandingin a Headstartpopulation. Journal of Experimental Child Psychology,63, 263-285.
Howes, C. (1988). Peerinteractionof young children. Monographs of the Societyfor Researchin Child Development,53 (Serial No. 217). Hughes,C. (1998). Executivefunction in preschoolersL: inks with the-
ory of mind and verbal ability. British Journal of Developmental
Psychology,16, 233-253.
Hughes,C., & Dunn, J. (1997). "Pretendyou didn't know": Young
children'stalk about mental statesin the context of pretendplay.
Cognitive Development,12, 477-499.
Huttenlocher,J., Haight, W., Bryk, A., Seltzer,M., & Lyons, T. (1991).
Early vocabularygrowth: Relationto languageinput andgender.De-
velopmentalPsychology,27, 236-248.
Imbens-Bailey,A. L., Prost, J. H., & Fabricius,W. V. (1997). Percep-
tion, desire and belief in me and you: Youngchildren's referenceto
mentalstatesin selfandothers.Manuscriptsubmittedfor publication. Jenkins,J. M., & Astington,J. W. (1996). Cognitivefactorsandfamily structureassociatedwith theory-of-minddevelopmentin youngchil-
dren.DevelopmentalPsychology,32, 70-78.
Leslie, A. (1987). PretenceandrepresentationT: he origins of "theory of mind." Psychological Review,94, 412-426.
Lewis,C.,Freeman,N.,Kyriakidou,C.,Maridaki-Kassotaki,K.,& Berridge,D. M. (1996). Thesocialbasisof theoryof mind: Influences of siblings and, more importantly, interactionswith adult kin. Child Development,67, 2930-2947.
MacWhinney,B., & Snow, C.E. (1985). The Child LanguageData ExchangeSystem.Journal of Child Language, 12, 271-295.
Mayes,L. C., Klin, A., Tercyak,K. P.,Jr.,Ciccetti,D. V., & Cohen,D. J. (1996). Test-retestreliability for false-belieftasks.Journal of Child andAdolescentPsychiatry,37, 313-319.
McCarthy,D. (1972). Manualfor theMcCarthyScalesfor Children's Abilities. New York: PsychologicalCorporation.
Moore, C., Bryant, D., & Furrow, D. (1989). Mental terms and the developmentof certainty. Child Development,60, 167-171.
Newcomb,A. E, & Bagwell, C. ( 1995). Children'sfriendshiprelations: A meta-analyticreview. Psychological Bulletin, 117,306-347.
Oswald, D. P., & Ollendick, T. (1989). Role taking and social compe- tencein autismandmentalretardation.Journal ofAutismandDevel- opmental Disorders, 19, 119-128.
Perner, J. (1996). Simulation as explication of predication-implicit knowledgeaboutthemind:Argumentsfor asimulation-theorymix. In P. Carruthers& P. K. Smith (Eds.), Theories of theory of mind (pp. 90-104). Cambridge,UK: CambridgeUniversityPress.
Perner, J., Ruffman, T., & Leekam, S.R. (1994). Theory of mind is contagious:You catch it from your sibs. Child Development, 65, 1228-1238.
Ruble, D. N., & Martin, C. L. (1998). Genderdevelopment.In W. Da- mon & N. Eisenberg(Eds.), Handbook of child psychology: Vol. 3. Social emotional and personality development (5th ed., pp. 933-
1016). New York: Wiley.
Russell,J., Mauthner,N., Sharpe,S., & Tidswell, T. ( 1991). The "win-
dows task" as a measureof strategicdeceptionin preschoolersand autistic subjects.British Journal of Developmental Psychology, 9, 301-314.
Shatz, M., Wellman, H.M., & Silber, S. (1983). The acquisition of mental verbs: A systematicinvestigationof the first referenceto a mental state. Cognition, 14, 301-321.
Slomkowski,C., & Dunn, J. (1996). Youngchildren'sunderstandingof o t h e r p e o p l e ' s b e l i e f s a n d f e e l i n g s a n d t h e i r c o n n e c t e dc o m m u n i c a t i o n with friends.DevelopmentalPsychology,32, 442-447.
Sodian, B., & Frith, U. (1992). Deception and sabotagein autistic, retardedandnormalchildren.Journal of Child PsychologyandPsy- chiatry, 33, 591-605.
Taylor,M., & Carlson,S. ( 1997). Therelationbetweenindividualdiffer- encesin fantasyand theory of mind. Child Development,60, 436- 455.
Wimmer, H., & Perner,J. (1983). Beliefs aboutbeliefs: Representation andconstrainingfunctionof wrongbeliefsin youngchildren'sunder- standingof deception.Cognition, 13, 103-128.
Youngblade, L., & Dunn, J. (1995). Individual differencesin young children'spretendplay with motherandsibling: Links to relationships andunderstandingof otherpeople'sfeelingsandbeliefs.Child Devel- opment,66, 1472-1492.
ReceivedJuly 1, 1997 Revision receivedJanuary25, 1998
AcceptedJanuary25, 1998 •
UNDERSTANDING MIND AND MENTAL-STATE TALK 1037
