Developmental Psychology Copyright 2008 by the American Psychological Association 2008, Vol. 44, No. 2, 618–623 0012-1649/08/$12.00 DOI: 10.1037/0012-1649.44.2.618
Infant Attention to Intentional Action Predicts Preschool Theory of Mind
Henry M. Wellman, Sarah Lopez-Duran, Jennifer LaBounty, and Betsy Hamilton University of Michigan
This research examines whether there are continuities between infant social attention and later theory of mind. Forty-five children were studied as infants and then again as 4-year-olds. Measures of infant social attention (decrement of attention during habituation to displays of intentional action) significantly predicted later theory of mind (false-belief understanding). Possibly, this longitudinal association could have been explained by more general developments in IQ, verbal competence, or executive function (rather than continuities in the realm of social cognition). However, the association remained significant and undiminished even when IQ, verbal competence, and executive function were controlled. The findings thus provide strong support for an important continuity in social cognition separable from continuities in more general information processing.
Keywords: theory of mind, infant cognition, developmental continuity
Two themes intertwine in contemporary cognitive developmen- tal theory: the emergence in infancy of basic understandings that may be continuous with later understanding (e.g., Spelke, Brein- linger, Macomber, & Jacobson, 1992), and the possible domain specificity of core areas of thought, such as language or theory of mind (e.g., Hirschfeld & Gelman, 1994). Classic infant continuity findings demonstrate an important association between infants’ attention to perceptual-object displays and later IQ; both infant habituation and dishabituation-novelty responses predict IQ at preschool (Bornstein & Sigman 1986). These perceptual-attention findings have been consistently interpreted as representing devel- opmental continuity in general information-processing capacities, such as memory encoding or executive functioning.
Infant looking-time paradigms can assess not only perception and memory but also infant knowledge within domains of under- standing, such as physical (e.g., Spelke et al., 1992) or social (e.g., Woodward, 1998) cognition. For social cognition, contemporary researchers have especially investigated infant recognition of in- tentional actions, actions that adults see as goal directed (with looking time [e.g., Gergely, Nadasdy, Csibra, & Biro, 1995; Woodward, 1998] and behavioral/imitation [e.g., Meltzoff, 1995; Tomasello & Haberl, 2003] paradigms). The assumption is that infant intentional understanding is precursory to later theory-of- mind understandings, such as preschoolers’ understandings of desire and then belief. If so, there should be discoverable connec-
Henry M. Wellman, Sarah Lopez-Duran, Jennifer LaBounty, and Betsy Hamilton, Department of Psychology, University of Michigan.
Sarah Lopez-Duran is now at the Department of Psychology, Bard College.
Funding for this research was provided by National Science Foundation Grant 0517872 and National Institute of Child Health & Human Develop- ment Grant 22149 to Henry M. Wellman. We thank the parents and children who participated.
Correspondence concerning this article should be addressed to Henry M. Wellman, Center for Human Growth and Development, University of Michigan, 300 North Ingalls, 10th Floor, Ann Arbor, MI 48109-0406. E-mail: hmw@umich.edu
tions between the two. Alternately, infants’ early analyses of action may be independent of intentional mental construals of actions that emerge later (e.g., Baldwin, Baird, Saylor, & Clark, 2001). Demonstrable continuity or discontinuity between infant and later social cognition would thus be important and informative. Intriguingly, Wellman, Phillips, Dunphy-Lelii, and LaLonde (2004) provided an initial social attention finding: Infant habitua- tion to human intentional action significantly predicted theory of mind at 4 years.
The Wellman et al. (2004) study examined infants’ understand- ing that a person looking positively at an object is likely to want it and so reach for it. In familiarization, thirty-two 14-month-olds (Phillips et al., 2002) saw a person look at one of two objects with an expression of interest and joy; then they saw two test events in which the person either reached for the “liked” object (consistent event) or the not-liked object (inconsistent event). Most infants (80%) looked longer at the inconsistent test event, as in other research (Gergely et al., 1995; Woodward, 1998) demonstrating infants’ developing understanding of intentional agents. Eighteen of these infants were tested as 4-year-olds on theory-of-mind tasks, including false-belief tasks but also a theory-of-mind scale (Well- man & Liu, 2004). Infant decrement of attention to the intentional action displays significantly predicted later theory of mind (r 􏰀 􏰁.55).
These data raise a provocative possibility: Social cognition may evidence distinctive infant-to-preschool continuities. Moreover, to the extent that social cognition constitutes a separate domain of developmental achievement (e.g., Wellman & Gelman, 1998), continuities in this domain could be separable from continuities in more general information processing. Indeed, distinctive develop- mental continuities could provide critical evidence supporting the domain specificity of theory-of-mind cognitions. While provoca- tive, the Wellman et al. (2004) findings are preliminary. The sample consisted of only 18 children; besides confirmation with a different sample, a larger sample is needed. McCall and Carriger (1993) showed that for infant perceptual-attention findings, larger samples often yield substantially smaller predictive correlations. Moreover, discrimination between social cognition and general
 618
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

information processing or developmental status is needed. Because infant attention (in perceptual-attention studies) reliably predicts later IQ, a “social-attention” finding may show only that more advanced infants do better on most cognitive tasks in preschool, including social–cognitive ones. Wellman et al. (2004) included a brief IQ measure (the Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test; Dunn & Dunn, 1997), and the relation between infant social attention and preschool theory of mind remained with that measure partialled out. A larger sample and consideration of other factors would allow firmer results. Of special importance are executive function and verbal competence (which develop alongside social cognition in early childhood). Language competence, including vocabulary (Jenkins & Astington, 1996), syntax (Astington & Jenkins, 1999), and conversational exchanges (Cutting & Dunn, 1999), substan- tially impacts theory-of-mind development, as do advances in executive function (Carlson & Moses, 2001).
Initial perceptual-attention findings from samples of 15 to 20 children showing correlations from .30 to .50 (e.g., Bornstein, 1985; Fagan & McGrath 1981) were unclear until replicated and extended. The initial social-attention finding also requires more definitive examination, extension, and test.
The Current Study
Several years ago, we tested 89 10- to 12-month-olds on a slightly different version of the same looking-time habituation-test task used in Wellman et al. (2004). We were able to retest 45 of them as 4-year-olds on several relevant measures.
Looking Time
Looking-time studies contain two informative measures (Born- stein & Sigman, 1986): decrements in attention during habituation/ familiarization and novelty preference during test trials. Both correlate to later IQ in perceptual-attention studies, yet Wellman et al. (2004) found significant correlation to preschool theory of mind only for decrement of attention. However, because 14-month-olds’ novelty preferences were consistently in the same direction, the range of preference scores was small (much smaller than the range for decrement scores). The current study included infants at a more transitional age (10–12 months) to encompass greater variability in novelty preference.
Theory of Mind
As in Wellman et al. (2004), we assessed preschool theory of mind with both a five-item theory-of-mind scale that captures a systematic progression of theory-of-mind insights (Wellman & Liu 2004) and a two-task false-belief composite. False-belief under- standing provides the most often used, standard assessment for preschool theory of mind (Wellman, Cross, & Watson 2001); Wellman et al. (2004) found higher correlations with a scale than for false belief alone.
Language and Performance
The Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence (WPPSI; Wechsler, 1989) or the Stanford-Binet (Terman & Mer- rill, 1973) are consistently used in infant perceptual-attention con- tinuity studies (see McCall & Carriger, 1993) rather than the
Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test. We used the WPPSI because it provides both verbal and performance measures, and WPPSI vo- cabulary is a frequently used measure of preschool verbal compe- tence.
Executive Function
Executive function encompasses several constructs (e.g., Zelazo, Carter, Reznick, & Frye, 1997), but inhibitory control yields the strongest relations to theory of mind (Carlson & Moses, 2001). It further deserves emphasis because inhibition of attention has been posited to be a general cognitive process underlying infant–child continuity (McCall, 1994; McCall & Mash, 1995). Two common assessments of preschool inhibitory control were used—Whisper and Bear/Dragon (Carlson & Moses 2001; Kochanska, Murray, Jacques, Koenig, & Vandergeest, 1996)—that intercorrelate well and load on a common factor among a battery of 10 similar tasks and measures (Carlson & Moses, 2001).
The current sample and measures allow a firm test for signifi- cant associations between infant social cognition and preschool theory of mind. Further, our preschool measures allow a compre- hensive test for whether such associations index more general relations between theory of mind and verbal competence, execu- tive function, and IQ or more specific links between infant and preschool social cognition.
Method
Participants
Eighty-nine infants aged 10 months 5 days to 12 months 22 days (M 􏰀 11 months 10 days) participated in the preferential looking task as part of a different study. Forty-five infants (21 boys, 24 girls) were retested soon after their 4th birthdays: 38 (84%) at 50 or 51 months, and 7 at 52 or 53 months (M 􏰀 51). Forty-two completed all tasks at 4 years; 2 completed all but Bear/Dragon, and 1 completed all but WPPSI Block Design. Most of the children (87%) were identified by their parents as Caucasian; the remainder were largely biracial. Most (84%) had annual family incomes of $40,000 or more.
Specific Measures
Our focal measures are described below. We also explored variations on these measures in follow-up analyses.
Infancy. During habituation, infants saw multiple trials (min- imum of 6, maximum of 10) of a person looking at one of two objects with an expression of interest and joy. During test, infants saw each of two different test events three times (total 􏰀 6 test trials). In consistent test events, the actor first looked positively at one of the two objects and then went on to hold that same object (consistent with an understanding that actors’ intentional actions are directed by their perceptual-emotional regard). In inconsistent test events, the actor first looked positively at one object but then went on to hold the other object. (Study 1 of Phillips et al., 2002, details the procedure for the infants in the current research; their Study 4 details procedures for the 14-month-olds tested in Well- man et al., 2004).
BRIEF REPORTS
619
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

620
BRIEF REPORT
Each infant received trials of the habituation scenario and then the test trials (three consistent and three inconsistent in alternating order). Measures of decrement of attention in our paradigm were based on the first six habituation trials because all infants had at least six trials. Subtracting infants’ fifth and sixth habituation trials from their first two trials yielded an average decrement of 7.56 s (range 􏰀 41.20 to –65.11 s). As recommended by Bornstein and Sigman (1986), we calculated a weighted difference score: the above difference divided by the sum of the first two habituation trials. This calculation (the weighted decrement score) yields a statistically stronger measure that correlates highly with the simple difference, r(44) 􏰀 .91, p 􏰂 .01.
Novelty preference (a comparison of the infant’s looking to novel over familiarized stimuli) was less straightforward in our paradigm. In studies of infant IQ (e.g., Colombo, Mitchell, O’Brien, & Horowitz, 1987; Rose, Feldman, & Wallace, 1988), novelty preference compares familiar test stimuli that are identical with those presented in habituation to novel stimuli that differ. In contrast, in contemporary studies of infants’ physical and social cognition (e.g., Spelke et al., 1992; Woodward, 1998)—including Wellman et al. (2004) and this study—both consistent and incon- sistent test events differ from habituation and thus, strictly speak- ing, are novel. In these paradigms, attention during habituation may be the more informative measure. Nonetheless, consider a straightforward preference score subtracting infant’s looking to the three inconsistent test events from their looking to consistent test events. For these 45 infants, this simple test preference score ranged from 18.38 to –24.52 s (substantially larger variation than Wellman et al., 2004, where the range was 2.88 to –7.92 s). Bornstein and Sigman (1986) recommend a preferred measure for novelty preference of looking to inconsistent events divided by looking to the consistent plus the inconsistent events. This weighted test preference score correlates highly with simple test preference, r(44) 􏰀 .92, p 􏰂 .01.
4 years. The 4-year-old battery included a theory-of-mind scale: five different tasks that capture an extended progression of developmental achievements. These tasks form a strict Guttman scale where in the years from 3 to 6 most children go from first succeeding on a single task (assessing understanding of desires) to successively succeeding on more and more of the tasks in a strict progression (Wellman & Liu, 2004). This five-item scale includes one false-belief task (false contents), as well as tasks assessing understanding of diversity of desires, diversity of beliefs, knowledge–ignorance, and hidden emotion. Scores are from 0 (passing none) to 5 (passing all). We administered an additional false-belief task (false locations) for each child to address false- belief understanding more specifically. Summing scores on both false-belief tasks (one from the scale plus this second task) pro- vided a false-belief composite.
For brevity we used two subscales of the WPPSI: Vocabulary (a verbal measure) and Block Design (a performance measure). Each 4-year-old also received two executive function tasks, one requir- ing verbal and one behavioral responses. Whisper (Kochanska et al., 1996) requires inhibiting a normal voice: Children see 10 cartoon characters, some well-known (e.g., Winnie the Pooh, Elmo) and some not (e.g., Instant Martian, Petunia the Pig). Children are inclined to blurt loudly the name of those they know. Scores (0 􏰀 talk/shout, 1 􏰀 talk/whisper mix, 2 􏰀 do nothing, 3 􏰀 whisper) were summed for each child. Bear/Dragon (Carlson &
Moses 2001)—slightly modified here as Dog/Dragon—is akin to “Simon says” where children either perform (if the “nice dog” speaks) or suppress (if the “mean dragon” speaks) various simple actions (“stick out your tongue”). Scores (0 􏰀 incorrect response, 1 􏰀 unrelated action, 2 􏰀 partial movement, 3 􏰀 correct response) were summed for each child. Children completed all tasks in a single session, beginning with the theory-of-mind scale and ending with WPPSI Block Design.
Results
Background Data
Table 1 shows descriptive data for the various measures. For all 89 infants, 50 (56%) looked longer at the inconsistent test events; for the 45 infants retested at 4 years, 24 (53%) did so. Thus, retested infants were very similar to the entire group of 89.
Consistent with prior research (Wellman et al. 2001), our young 4-year-olds often failed false-belief tasks (averaging 32% correct) but exhibited substantial individual variation. Even when failing false belief, children exhibited emerging theory-of-mind knowl- edge. On the five-item scale, children averaged essentially three items correct—a score that represents understanding of desires and beliefs just shy of false-belief understanding. Again, individuals differed substantially.
Performance on the WPPSI was also age appropriate (in age- equivalent scores these 51-month-olds averaged 51 months for Vocabulary and 56 months for Block Design). Children performed well on the executive function tasks but with substantial variation (typical of young 4-year-olds; see Carlson & Moses 2001)—for example, ranging from 12 to 30 for Dog/Dragon.
Table 2 shows the correlations between the various preschool measures. As expected, these measures showed considerable over- lap, consistent with prior research; 2 out of 6 correlations exceeded conventional significance levels.
Table 1
Descriptive Data
 Participant Infants
4-year-olds
Data
Percent of infants looking longer to the inconsistent test event: 53%
Weighted decrement score: M 􏰀 .22 (SD 􏰀 .61), range 􏰀 􏰃1.83 to .83 (0 􏰀 no decrement)
Weighted test preference score: M 􏰀 .50 (SD 􏰀 .13), range 􏰀 .21 to .76 (out of possible 1.00)
False belief composite: M 􏰀 .64 (SD 􏰀 .77), range 􏰀 0 to 2.0 (out of possible 2.0)
Theory-of-Mind Scale score: M 􏰀 2.96 (SD 􏰀 .98), range 􏰀 1 to 5 (out of possible 5)
WPPSI Vocabulary: M 􏰀 15.44 (SD 􏰀 5.51), range 􏰀 3 to 25 (out of possible 47)
WPPSI Block Design: M 􏰀 17.28 (SD 􏰀 7.07), range 􏰀 2 to 31 (out of possible 42)
Inhibitory control, Dog/Dragon: M 􏰀 28.79 (SD 􏰀 3.60), range 􏰀 12 to 30 (out of possible 30)
Inhibitory control, Whisper: M 􏰀 28.18 (SD 􏰀 2.81), range 17 to 30 (out of possible 30)
  Note. WPPSI 􏰀 Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence.
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

Table 2
Correlations Among Preschool Measures
Variable 1234 1. False-belief composite —
remained nonsignificant between decrement of attention and the theory-of-mind scale and between test preference and false belief or the scale.
Several analyses help confirm this key finding. For example, although most children did well on the executive function testing, these tasks yielded sufficient variation to correlate substantially with the theory-of-mind scale and the WPPSI composite (see Table 2). That available variation could have significantly de- creased the correlation between decrement of attention and false belief but did not. Further, the key correlations represent more than a handful of outliers. Consider children in the top, middle, and bottom thirds of the distribution for attention decrement scores. Children in the top third averaged 1.13 on the false-belief com- posite, whereas children in the bottom third averaged 0.27, t(14) 􏰀 3.53, p 􏰂 .002. There were no differences between top and bottom thirds for the WPPSI or executive function composites, ts 􏰅 1.6, ps 􏰄 .12.
Discussion
Over the past 15 years, researchers have documented the im- pressive theory-of-mind competencies of preschoolers (e.g., Well- man et al., 2001) and toddlers (e.g., Repacholi & Gopnik, 1997). What are the origins of this childhood mentalistic social cognition? And do those origins lie solely in general information processing capacities (e.g., Cohen, 1998) or at least in part in specialized social– cognitive conceptions and capacities? Our findings directly address these timely, and classic, issues.
With 45 infants and multiple measures, we confirm and clarify a substantial, longitudinal link between infant attention to human action and later theory of mind. Several features of the research and the accumulating findings deserve emphasis: (a) The associ- ation holds consistently for decrement of attention, not novelty preference, and is most predictive of later false-belief understand- ing. (b) It holds across several infant ages and task variations. (c) It is robust (r 􏰀 .40 –.50) and remains robust when various indexes of more general information processing are controlled.
Specifically, Wellman et al. (2004) found a correlation between infant social attention and 4-year-olds’ performance on a false- belief composite (r 􏰀 􏰁.35) for eighteen 14-month-olds and a more substantial correlation with performance on a theory-of-mind scale (r 􏰀 􏰁.55). Aiming to replicate Wellman et al. (2004), Aschersleben, Hofer, and Jovanovic (in press) found a similar correlation between infant attention to goal-directed action and 4-year-old false-belief performance (􏰁.45) for 20 German 6-month-olds (and a nonsignificant relation to theory-of-mind scale scores of 􏰁.10). The current 45 infants more than doubled either previous sample and yielded a substantial correlation for false-belief performance (􏰁.40) and a nonsignificant correlation with theory-of-mind scale scores (􏰁.15) for 10- to 12-month-olds. The relation between infant social attention and later theory of mind is thus especially consistent and robust for false-belief per- formances, given that preschool theory of mind is measured at just about 4 years (for all three studies, M 􏰀 50–51 months). This relation remains essentially undiminished when measures of more general cognitive processes are controlled. Of course, any single control is limited: Wellman et al. (2004) used a single measure of verbal IQ (Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test); Aschersleben et al. (in press) used a single composite measure of language compe-
2. Theory-of-mind scale
3. WPPSI composite
4. Inhibitory control composite
† * **
p 􏰂 .10. p 􏰂 .05. p 􏰂 .01.
Longitudinal Analyses
.49** —
.18 .22
—
*†
.10 .37 .27 —
BRIEF REPORTS
621
   The key results concern relations between infant looking mea- sures and later theory of mind. Because the age span between youngest and oldest infants was 10 weeks (sizable for infants aged approximately 44 weeks), all longitudinal analyses controlled for days of age at infant testing. Focally, for decrement of attention (the weighted decrement score), infant looking correlated to the false-belief composite, r(42) 􏰀 .38, p 􏰂 .05. Infant decrement of attention did not correlate with theory-of-mind scale scores, r(42) 􏰀 .14, ns. For novelty preference (weighted test preference score), infant preferences did not correlate with the false-belief composite, r(42) 􏰀 .02, and did not correlate with theory-of-mind scale scores, r(42) 􏰀.12.
Supplemental analyses confirmed that these results were appar- ent in multiple complementary measures. Thus, decrement of attention calculated with a simple difference score correlated sub- stantially with false belief (.36, p 􏰂 .05), just as with the weighted score. No alternative decrement of attention scoring correlated with theory-of-mind scale scores. No alternative novelty- preference measures correlated with either false belief or the scale. For example, a measure of attention recovery (subtracting infants’ 3 inconsistent test trials from their last 3 habituation trials) failed to correlate with false belief: r(42)􏰀.07. Use of Spearman’s rank correlation (treating the false-belief composite as nonparametric), confirmed the above pattern: significant correlation between dec- rement of attention and false belief (.44, p 􏰂 .01) but not between test preference and false belief (.15, ns). Finally, the theory-of- mind scale captures children’s responses to a range of tasks, from easiest (diverse desires) to hardest (hidden emotion) with knowledge–ignorance in the middle and false-belief one step harder than that (Wellman & Liu 2004). For this age (where most children pass the easiest and fail the hardest tasks) infant attention related to passing or failing the “middle” tasks—the weighted decrement score failed to correlate to diverse desires (.03, ns) or hidden emotion (.04, ns) but correlated to a three-task composite that included knowledge–ignorance along with false belief (.37, p 􏰂 .05).
Thus, we found substantial associations between infant social attention during habituation and preschool theory of mind as indexed by false belief. Can this association be explained by verbal competence, performance competence (or a combination of the two representing overall IQ), and/or executive function? When we simultaneously controlled for age at infant testing, WPPSI Vocab- ulary, WPPSI Block Design, and both executive function tasks, the relation between infant decrement of attention and preschool false belief remained significant, r(35) 􏰀 .38, p 􏰂 .05, for the weighted score (and also for the simple difference score). Relationships
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

622
BRIEF REPORT
tence (the SETK; Grimm, 2001). Verbal competence, general IQ, and executive function are all important: Each focuses on comple- mentary aspects of general information processing that make sub- stantial and independent contributions to preschool theory-of-mind performance. Our findings demonstrate a continuity from infant social attention to preschool theory of mind with all three factors measured and controlled.
This social– cognitive continuity is consistently evident for mea- sures of attention during habituation but not (yet) for other infant measures. For example, Olineck and Poulin-DuBois (2007) found no relation between imitation of intentional actions at 14 or 18 months and later false-belief or theory-of-mind scale scores. And, in current looking-time research, novelty preference has not pre- dicted later theory of mind. In Wellman et al. (2004) and As- chersleben et al. (in press), novelty preference scores had reduced variance because the infants were tested at ages where the vast majority preferred one of the two test events. The current data thus provide a more adequate test, more convincingly showing predic- tive relations for decrement of attention and not novelty prefer- ence. Earlier infant IQ continuity findings made this lack of association with novelty preference unexpected. However, meth- odological differences (as noted in the Method section) may play an important role. Moreover, our data now suggest that an analogy to the infant IQ findings may be misleading because social atten- tion yields distinctive continuities, separable from IQ or general information processing. That infants’ attention to intentional- action displays during habituation, as measured by decrement of attention, is specially revealing makes conceptual sense. This indexes infants’ ability to parse displays meaningfully during initial exposure to them; that is, differences on this measure represent differences in processing or interest as infants come to a stable, intentional impression of the displayed action. That other measures have proven unrevealing is less interpretable and less certain. The full pattern of continuities from infant intentional understandings to later theory of mind is an important topic for future research.
The infant tasks in these studies all displayed live human actors engaged in clearly intentional action, perceiving and reaching for goal objects. Thus, the focal social attention is specifically infant attention to intentional goal-directed action. The data are thus consistent with the following specific social continuity hypothesis: An important form of social cognition develops in infancy, revolv- ing around understanding of human agents as intentional, goal- directed beings, and this understanding develops into preschool understanding of persons as mental beings. These social– cognitive developments produce continuities in the realm of theory of mind separable from continuities in the realm of perceptual-object cog- nition and general information processing or IQ. A definitive test of such a hypothesis would test the same infants on contrasting perceptual-attention and social-attention tasks, and then test them on IQ, on measures of general information processing, on theory of mind, and on physical object cognition as preschoolers.
Even in advance of further tests, however, the current data (having controlled IQ, verbal competence, and executive function) provide clear support for this social–cognitive continuity hypoth- esis. These findings do not disconfirm hypotheses that some infant action understandings (other ones, or those emerging in still younger infants) may be independent of later intentional-mental construals, but they do help confirm hypotheses (e.g., Tomasello
Carpenter, Call, Behne, & Moll, 2005; Wellman, 1993; Wood- ward, 1998) that early understanding of intentional action is an important wellspring for later theory of mind. The data also help validate several looking-time paradigms as indeed capturing un- derstandings continuous with and informative for later theory of mind.
References
Aschersleben, G., Hofer, T., & Jovanovic, B. (in press). Does infant action interpretation predict later theory of mind abilities? Developmental Science.
Astington, J. W., & Jenkins, J. M. (1999). A longitudinal study of the relation between language and theory-of-mind development. Develop- mental Psychology, 35, 1311–1320.
Baldwin, D. A., Baird, J. A., Saylor, M. M., & Clark, M. A. (2001). Infants parse dynamic action. Child Development, 73, 708–717.
Bornstein, M. H. (1985). Habituation of attention as a measure of visual information processing in human infants: Summary, systematization, and synthesis. In G. Gottleib & N. A. Krasnegor (Eds.), Measurement of audition and vision in the first year of postnatal life: A methodological overview (pp. 253–300). Norwood, NJ: Ablex.
Bornstein, M. H., & Sigman, M. D. (1986). Continuity in mental devel- opment from infancy. Child Development, 57, 251–274.
Carlson, S. M., & Moses, L. J. (2001). Individual differences in inhibitory control and children’s theory of mind. Child Development, 72, 1032– 1053.
Cohen, L. (1998). An information-processing approach to infant perception and cognition. In F. Simion & G. Butterworth (Eds.), The development of sensory, motor and cognitive capacities in early infancy: From perception to cognition (pp. 277–300). Hove, England: Psychology Press.
Colombo, J., Mitchell, D. W., O’Brien, M., & Horowitz, F. D. (1987). The stability of visual habituation in the first year. Child Development, 58, 474 – 487.
Cutting, A. L., & Dunn, J. (1999). Theory of mind, emotion understanding, language, and family background. Child Development, 70, 853–865. Dunn, L. M., & Dunn, L. C. (1997). PPVT-III: Peabody Picture Vocabu-
lary Test—Third Edition. Circle Pines, MN: American Guidance Ser-
vice.
Fagan, J. F., & McGrath, S. K. (1981). Infant recognition memory and later
intelligence. Intelligence, 5, 121–130.
Gergely, G., Nadasdy, Z., Csibra, G., & Biro, S. (1995). Taking the
intentional stance at 12 months of age. Cognition, 56, 165–193. Grimm, H. (2001). Language development test for 3- to 5-year-old children
[SETK 3–5]. Gottingen, Germany: Hogrefe.
Hirschfeld, L. A., & Gelman, S. A. (1994). Mapping the mind: Domain
specificity in cognition and culture. New York: Cambridge University
Press.
Jenkins, J. M., & Astington, J. W. (1996). Cognitive, linguistic, and social
factors associated with theory of mind development in young children.
Developmental Psychology, 32, 70–78.
Kochanska, G., Murray, K., Jacques, T. Y., Koenig, A. L., & Vandergeest,
K. A. (1996). Inhibitory control in young children and its role in
emerging internalization. Child Development, 67, 490–507.
McCall, R. B. (1994). What processes mediate prediction of childhood IQ from infant habituation and recognition memory? Intelligence, 18, 107–
125.
McCall, R. B., & Carriger, M. S. (1993). A meta-analysis of infant
habituation and recognition memory performance as predictors of later
IQ. Child Development, 64, 57–79.
McCall, R. B., & Mash, C. W. (1995). Infant cognition and its relation to
mature intelligence. Annals of Child Development, 10, 27–56. Meltzoff, A. N. (1995). Understanding the intentions of others: Re-
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.

enactment of intended acts by 18-month-old children. Developmental
Psychology, 31, 838–850.
Olineck, K. M., & Poulin-DuBois, D. (2007). Imitation of intentional
actions and internal state language in infancy predict preschool theory of
mind skills. European Journal of Developmental Psychology, 4, 14–30. Phillips, A. T., Wellman, H. M., & Spelke, E. S. (2002). Infants’ ability to connect gaze and emotional expression to intentional action. Cognition,
85, 53–78.
Repacholi, B. M., & Gopnik, A. (1997). Early reasoning about desires:
Evidence from 14- and 18-month-olds. Developmental Psychology, 33,
12–21.
Rose, S. A., Feldman, J. F., & Wallace, I. F. (1988). Individual differences
in infants information processing: Reliability, stability, prediction. Child
Development, 59, 1177–1197.
Spelke, E. S., Breinlinger, K., Macomber, J., & Jacobson, K. (1992).
Origins of knowledge. Psychological Review, 99, 605–632.
Terman, L. M., & Merrill, M. A. (1973). Stanford–Binet Intelligence Scale.
Boston: Houghton-Mifflin.
Tomasello, M., Carpenter, M., Call, J., Behne, T., & Moll, H. (2005).
Understanding and sharing intentions: The origins of cultural learning.
Behavior & Brain Sciences, 28, 675–735.
Tomasello, M., & Haberl, K. (2003). Understanding attention: 12- and
18-month-olds know what is new for other persons. Developmental
Psychology, 39, 906–912.
Wechsler, D. (1989). Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence—
Revised. San Antonio, TX: Psychological Corporation.
Wellman, H. M. (1993). Early understanding of mind: The normal case. In S. Baron-Cohen, H. Tager-Flusberg, & D. Cohen (Eds.), Understanding other minds: Perspectives from autism (pp. 10–39). Oxford, England: Oxford University Press.
Wellman, H. M., Cross, D., & Watson, J. (2001). Meta-analysis of theory of mind development: The truth about false belief. Child Development, 72, 655–684.
Wellman, H. M., & Gelman, S. A. (1998). Knowledge acquisition in foundational domains. In D. Kuhn & R. Siegler (Eds.), Cognition, perception and language: Vol. 2. Handbook of child psychology (5th ed., pp. 523–573). New York: Wiley.
Wellman, H. M., & Liu, D. (2004). Scaling of theory of mind tasks. Child Development, 75, 523–541.
Wellman, H. M., Phillips, A. T., Dunphy-Lelii, S., & LaLonde, N. (2004). Infant social attention predicts preschool social cognition. Developmen- tal Science, 7, 283–288.
Woodward, A. (1998). Infants selectively encode the goal object of an actor’s reach. Cognition, 69, 1–34.
Zelazo, P. D., Carter, A., Reznick, J. S., & Frye, D. (1997). Early devel- opment of executive function: A problem-solving framework. Review of General Psychology, 1, 1–29.
Received September 29, 2006 Revision received August 2, 2007
Accepted August 21, 2007 􏰆
BRIEF REPORTS
623
This document is copyrighted by the American Psychological Association or one of its allied publishers. This article is intended solely for the personal use of the individual user and is not to be disseminated broadly.
